<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Achieving comity: disciplinary border crossings with Guy Aston</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard</author>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Talk given at SSLMIT, Forli, 12 April 2019</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Drafted in OpenOffice and converted to TEI XML</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change when="2019-04-21"> final tidying up</change>
            <change when="2019-04-11">convert from ODT</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="text" rend="P21">
            <head>Achieving comity: disciplinary border crossings with Guy Aston</head>
            <p>We soon learn and soon forget that academic life is inescapably fractured, with
               different disciplines competing for our allegiance like rival fiefdoms. Part of the
               painful process of growing up is recognizing which of them provides the most
               congenial home for us, that is, which discipline best accepts whichever of the many
               identities we have necessarily been experimenting with throughout our adolescence.
               When, on meeting a new acquaintance we ask “and what do you do?”, we expect to be
               told not just their hierarchical status (I’m a researcher/ professor/ lecturer/
               technician) but also their disciplinary credentials, names which are themselves signs
               of tribal affiliation. Only a qualified practitioner of (shall we say) “Data-Driven
               Discourse Analysis” or “English for Academic Purposes” or “Computer Assisted Language
               Learning” can determine whether a random acquaintance is truly of the same
               persuasion, a dangerous radical, a would-be disciple, or merely a bluffer. But the
               names are what matter. Deciding what it is that you really want to do, what it is
               that you really think, cannot be done in isolation, nor can it go unlabelled. You
               must find a distinctive name in terms of which to define yourself, making clear what
               you have in common with existing tribes and where you beg to differ: you must declare
               your <ref target="#slide1" rend="color(#ce181e)"> allegiance </ref> -- or lack of it. </p>
            <p>This is why it is difficult for truly interdisciplinary studies to gain a foothold in
               the academy, and also why, when they do, they risk succumbing to fossilisation as a
               new entrenched orthodoxy.</p>
            <p>
               <ref target="#slide2">In this paper,</ref> I am trying to cross frontiers in various
               ways. I will use graphics and bullet points in my presentation, as I do when
               teaching, but the bulk of my argument will be in discursive prose, of the kind I
               would normally prefer to read silently. I will present some material as if it were
               part of a course in sociology or history : this is how we used to persuade people to
               use corpora, or the BNC, or computers more generally, and these are the tools we had
               at our disposal. How quaint! How naive! But I will also try to show how Guy’s
               attitude to that necessary pedagogy enriched and complemented the activity, and I
               hope persuade you that his approach has more long-lasting implications and
               relevance.</p>
            <p>I <ref target="#slide3">first met Guy in 1965 </ref> when we were both making the
               transition from smart lad at a good school to idiot freshman at an Oxford college. We
               enjoyed a close and more or less continuous friendship from then until his untimely
               death last year, experiencing together many of the mundane but essential rituals of
               growing up – getting a job, finding a place to live, finding a partner, celebrating
               birthdays and other significant milestones, and so on, and so on. But I am going to
               talk more about the professional components of our relationship than the personal
               ones, inextricably intertwingled though the two were. As how could they not be,
               since, as I have remarked before, Guy made a point of transforming his professional
               relationships into personal ones wherever possible. I want to focus on the period
               from about 1992 to 2007, during which our separate academic paths converged, and some
               effects of that convergence.</p>
            <p>In October 1992 I spoke at a workshop in Parma, at the invitation of John Morley
               though actually (I suspect) instigated by Guy. The gig was to talk about the
               wonderful new world of “Electronic Resources for Textual Studies” and to persuade a
               skeptical audience just how much fun they could be having with their computers,
               beyond simply writing essays on them. <ref target="#slide4">(here I am doing it)
               </ref>I recently found a write up I subsequently contributed to “Textus” from which I
               quote: ‘... you can use electronic texts to substantiate your subjective impressions
               about the nature of the language. In teaching, they provide an enormous wealth of
               information about usage: there is nothing as good as an example(except two examples).
               And electronic texts are also invaluable as the raw material of other projects, in
               the creation of multimedia teaching tools with which students can interact, or simply
               as a basis for cheap publication. For all of this to be possible, of course, there is
               a need for standardization -- but that is another lecture.’</p>
            <p>Amongst many other things, most of which have long since vanished, this article does
               mention the forthcoming availability of something called the British National Corpus,
               but the occasion was chiefly memorable to me because it was over an excellent dinner
               (almost certainly featuring varieties of ham) that I was made quite clearly to
               understand that all this talk of a global electronic village was all very well, but
               there was a professionalism in academia, that these were serious people, and you
               needed a doctorate to express an opinion about how language worked in their company.
               Fair enough, in retrospect: I was definitely guilty of a bumptious amateurism, a
               necessary consequence of my evangelical desire to convert the world to SGML. And this
               did not, I must confess, lessen over the next few years. Over the next few years, as
               head of the Humanities Computing Unit at Oxford I popped up to harangue innocent
               academics at all sorts of venues – <ref target="#slide5">making a pitch</ref> for the
               British National Corpus, for the Text Encoding Initiative, for something mysterious
               called Digital Resources in the Humanities, and so on and so on. My carbon footprint
               (already inflated during the production of the TEI) became seriously overweight; my
               addiction to the headily addictive work of standards definition showed no sign of
               diminishing. <ref target="#slide6">Here I am</ref>, for example, pitching for the TEI
               at the venerable Haiensa monastery in Korea, in the autumn of 1994. I found I was
               mutating into a large-ish fish in an admittedly small pond of self-appointed experts
               in a pleasantly obscure domain: the sort of thing you could guarantee would cause
               people’s eyes to glaze over were they incautious enough to ask “and what do you do
               exactly?” Fortunately, Guy was around to remind me that the usefulness of a digital
               resource had a lot more to do with its accessibility than its sophistication.</p>
            <p>In April 1994, I was in Lancaster for what we did not then know would become the
               first of a long lasting biennial series of conferences on Teaching and Language
               Corpora. I was there mostly to show solidarity with colleagues at Lancaster, who
               appeared to think there might be some interest in the use of language corpora in
               language teaching as distinct from language research. To put this in context it is
               noteworthy that the <ref target="#slide7">original design criteria for the BNC,
                  stated </ref>
               <ref target="#slide8">or unstated</ref> were predicated on the assumption that a 100
               million word corpus of current English, spoken and written, selected according to
               defined sampling principles, and uniformly encoded would mostly be of interest to NLP
               researchers and other similarly serious people, beyond of course its core target
               audience, the professional lexicographers and dictionary makers who had financed it,
               and the researchers in corpus linguistics who had constructed it. And even this
               “outreach” as we did not then call it, came about because it was necessary to address
               the interests of the scientific communities funded by SERC, the Science and
               Engineering Research Council, in order to secure additional funding from the
               Department of Trade and Industry. Government funding was also (incidentally) why the
               regrettable word “National” appears in its title, not being then entirely sullied by
               association with “nationalism”. Follow the money is always a good maxim when trying
               to understand history. Anyway. Conspicuously missing from the list of target users
               for the BNC were those who within five years of its release became its primary users:
               the language teaching community, in particular but not exclusively, those working
               with non-native speakers of English, whether as teachers, researchers, or
               learners.</p>
            <p>The TaLC conference could be thought of as an attempt to rectify that omission,
               building as it did on the tradition of “data driven learning” associated with Tim
               Johns and other pioneers from Birmingham University. Guy gave a rather good paper
               about how he had been using digitized newspapers as corpora in teaching – CDs
               containing most of the text of several current newspapers were just becoming
               available at that time, as were a number of other interesting fore-runners of today’s
               digital collections. But what that first conference demonstrated overall was how much
               proselytising remained to be done. Although wonderful resources like the BNC were
               available, the communities which stood most to benefit from their use remained
               uninformed – when they were not actively hostile to the technical aspects of doing
               so.</p>
            <p>In March 1995, en route to a meeting in Pisa for a deservedly forgotten EU Project
               called Memoria, I met up with Guy in Florence. My visit report of the time remarks:
               “I went to Florence, partly for touristic reasons, but mainly to persuade my old
               friend Dr A to write the BNC Handbook for me, which I duly did over an excellent
               lunch in an obscure, but very crowded fiaschetteria. This was the sort of Italian
               eating establishment I like -- hams hanging from the ceiling, elbow-to-elbow diners
               all shouting at the top of their voices, small children misbehaving with indulgent
               grandparents, plates of food and bottles of chianti flying everywhere. ”</p>
            <p>The proposition I put to Guy was to work with me on producing something better than
               the sort of computer manual which stays on the shelf. Over that excellent lunch we
               worked out a cunning plan. The book should consist of a series of carefully scripted
               tutorials, each one focussing on a different and linguistically-interesting question.
               The tutorials would show with precise instructions how to solve, or at least how to
               explore solutions for the stated problem using the Windows-based software we had
               developed at Oxford to search the BNC. (This was called SARA – for SGML Aware
               Retrieval Application – and entirely by coincidence my second daughter’s first name).
               My part was to help write introductory chapters explaining what the BNC was and what
               the software did, and also to test drive the tutorials as they took shape. Guy’s part
               was to produce the linguistically interesting questions, to explore how they might be
               addressed using SARA, and to consider other avenues of enquiry they opened up. <ref
                  target="#slide9">Here’s a nice photo I found</ref> of him doing so. </p>
            <p>I also persuaded Guy that we would produce our manuscript in the recently defined TEI
               SGML format, using descriptive rather than presentational markup, which added a
               satisfyingly geeky additional layer to the project. It also required me to find ways
               of generating nicely formatted pages from the SGML input, and required Guy to
               introduce meaningful SGML tagging into his pellucid prose, <ref target="#slide10">
                  like this</ref>
            </p>
            <p>For the next couple of years therefore, we grappled together with such classic
               conundrums as “Do Men Say Mauve”? And “When is ajar not a door?” . Reviewing the text
               today (you can still find a bootlegged copy of it online if you try hard enough) I am
               struck by the freshness of the pedagogic approach it takes and the way the reader is
               treated as a co-conspirator rather than a passive recipient of instruction. Of
               course, it is now a common orthodoxy to talk up exploratory teaching methods, but I
               don’t know of many instructional manuals from that period which do it so thoroughly.
               In this respect, the <title>Handbook</title> demonstrated clearly Guy’s pedagogic
               principles. Teacher and learner alike seek to achieve comity in a slightly
               unfamiliar, data-rich, curiously fascinating environment.</p>
            <p>Somewhat to our surprise, the BNC Handbook <ref target="#slide11"> (finally published
                  by Edinburgh University Press </ref> in December 1997) sold rather well, at least,
               until new versions of both the BNC and its software appeared at the end of the 20th
               century, thus rendering the practical parts of the Handbook entirely useless. We did
               periodically consider that it might be nice to produce a new updated edition, but the
               pressure of other work and (let’s be honest) a lack of relish for retreading old
               material kept us from doing so. Even more improbably, the Handbook was translated
               into Japanese shortly after it became definitively outdated by events.</p>
            <p>As I may have already mentioned, my tendencies to evangelism were at their peak at
               this time. Having endured them himself, Guy hit on the idea of offering me the
               opportunity to indulge them further by inviting me to run a “TEI training workshop”
               here in Forli, almost exactly 22 years ago, from 14 to 23 April, 1997, and I am
               delighted to see that some of those who survived the experience are with us here
               today, apparently unscarred though perhaps less youthful than they appear in <ref
                  target="#slide12">this historic daguerrotype.</ref>
            </p>
            <p>This first Forli workshop consisted of eight 90 minute lectures, three two hour
               practical sessions, and two discussion sessions, somehow squeezed into six days of
               fairly concentrated effort. It began with lectures on the motivation for encoding and
               the varieties, benefits, and dangers of markup, before launching into a presentation
               of what was then known as “document analysis”, followed by an exercise in which
               students were invited to do some. My report of the workshop says drily “The
               discussion was a little inhibited at this stage, as many of the students were still
               reeling from the shock of being asked to consider using a computer for something
               other than word processing.” The reeling may be assumed to have contined the next
               day, which apparently included “<hi rend="italic">a whistle-stop tour through the
                  syntax of SGML, requiring considerable amounts of stamina</hi>” before introducing
               the TEI schema itself and letting the students experience a real-life SGML-aware
               editor called Author Editor.</p>
            <p> Expository lectures on the TEI Architecture, the TEI Header, and a variety of TEI
               tools, followed, but I am pretty sure that it was the three two hour practicals which
               made the whole thing bearable. I learned a great deal about how to teach such
               material from this experience, in particular, the importance of leavening or
               complementing the technical presentations with ample opportunities for students to
               experience directly for themselves what the technology could do, whether under the
               guidance of a scripted exercise, or an open-ended exploration.</p>
            <p>This is apparent in the <ref target="#slide13">programmes of subsequent TEI workshops
               </ref>(there were 7 in all, in May 98, Dec 99, May 2001, April 2003, June 2004, and
               March 2006) , which placed a much greater emphasis on practical work, and, crucially,
               on practical work using as raw material precisely the sort of textual resources which
               participants were likely to beworking with already, and which they might themselves
               provide. In other TEI workshops, which tended to attract more diverse groups of
               specialists, this was not always possible: researchers in mediaeval literature found
               it needlessly difficult to consider the markup of 19th century postcards, for
               example. For the language focussed students at Forli, all was grist to the mill, not
               only the 19th century periodical but also the contemporary web page, the transcribed
               TV show, the radio interview and so on. Moreover, by 2001, it had become entirely
               reasonable to require of the participants that they “should have basic computing
               skills (web browsing, word processing etc.) and a willingness to grapple with
               alphabet soup” – since that was precisely what they did all the time.</p>
            <p>Where the BNC had been designed as a surrogate for the whole of the English language,
               in some rather ill defined sense, I learned in Forli that there was also a place for
               smaller corpora which represented very specific kinds of language use. The creation
               of such “idiolectal” corpora had obvious attractions for student interpreters in
               particular, since it gave them a way of rapidly identifying lexical or idiomatic
               patterns characteristic of particular usage domains, such as weather reports, or the
               antiques trade, or political discussion, or even gothic novels. (I apologise, a
               little belatedly, for insisting on using <title>Varney the Vampyre</title> as my
               vehicle for showing how to index a corpus with Xaira). </p>
            <p rend="color(#800000)bold italic">[slide 14]</p>
            <p> My diary shows that Guy and I spent much of the next decade perfecting a <ref
                  target="#slide14">double act</ref>, in which I would introduce and/or market the
               latest version of the BNC, and he would demonstrate its exemplary qualities as a
               teaching aid in the classroom. He would highlight how this approach might do away
               with any need for problematic “teacher intuition” about language, placing native and
               non-native speaking teachers on an equal footing, and above all engaging directly
               with the learner. Find out about the language and the culture for yourself! Form
               hypotheses and test them! And, perhaps rather cheekily, “be ready to contradict your
               teacher”.</p>
            <p>With some trepidation, let me remind you of some of the salient features of this
               Astonian approach. My first example is an exploration of the word <ref
                  target="#slide16">fallback</ref> with <ref target="#slide17">serendipitous
                  outcomes</ref>
            </p>
            <p>My second example demonstrates how Guy was always ready to exploit data complexity,
               taking full advantage of the markup in later versions of the BNC to explore the
                  word<ref target="#slide18"> tend.</ref>
            </p>
            <p>We took this message to many different venues. We spoke at the British Association
               for Applied Linguistics (Southampton in 1995 and Reading 1999); we spoke at
               TaLC-inspired conferences such as “Practical Applications of Language Corpora” (Lodz
               in April 1997 and again in 1999) and “Language Learning and Computers” in Chemnitz in
               February 1998. To celebrate the millenium we took our double act to the “2nd North
               American Symposium on Corpus Linguistics” (University of Northern Arizona, Flagstaff,
               April 2000), which also gave us an excuse to <ref target="#slide19">visit the Grand
                  Canyon</ref> (by train, of course). We organized a session on corpus linguistics
               at a meeting of ESSE in Helsinki in August 2000; we spoke at ICAME – the big daddy of
               all corpus linguistics conferences – in Stratford in 2007; we taught a “Methods
               Network” workshop in Oxford, jointly organized with Ylva Berglund in November 2007
               and repeated in February 2008.</p>
            <p> And of course we participated in <ref target="#slide20">the biennial TaLC
                  conferences, </ref> from 1996 to 2010, by which time Guy (at least) had become a
               rather benign elder statesman figure rather than an <foreign>enfant
                  terrible</foreign>. If you’re interested in the evolution of that conference,
               there is a document somewhere on the Internet which lists all the locations, the
               programmes, and even the abstracts (some of them still online; others requiring an
               excursion to the Wayback Machine); it also provides links to the various edited
               proceedings volumes, a skim through which yields some possibly interesting
               conclusions. </p>
            <p>From Lancaster in 1996 to Cambridge in 2018, by way of Oxford (1998), Graz (2000),
               Bologna/Bertinoro (2002) , Granada (2004), Paris (2006), Lisbon (2008), Brno
               (2010), Warsaw (2012), Lancaster again (2014), and Giessen (2016), there is ample
               meat here for the kind of meta-analysis that characterizes interdisciplinary
               activities in the throes of consolidation. The results of that analysis (there is a
               good example by Alex Boulton in the most recent TaLC) tend to confirm that yes, it is
               a good idea to use language corpora in language teaching, and point to a <ref
                  target="#slide21"> broadly similar set of benefits </ref> that <ref
                  target="#slide22">such usage </ref>can bring. </p>
            <p>And yet, TaLC practitioners, some of them, also continue to have reservations about
               the ease with which traditional language teaching methods can accommodate the full
               corpus-based, learner-centred, comity-seeking approach that Guy adumbrated thirty
               years ago. The tools are slicker and more professional, the range and scope of
               available corpora is magnified beyond recognition, the sense of community amongst
               those practitioners at all levels is stronger than ever, but some things do not
               change. Like every other academic tribe before them, perhaps, today’s corpus lovers
               have a self-definition that depends on the existence of an opposing unregenerate
               tribe of old-fashioned obstructionists. Whatever the reason, every meta-analysis
               points to the need to continue the struggle of opening minds to new (actually not so
               new now) ways of engaging with the technology.</p>
            <p>By which I do not mean simply using it, but doing so in an informed way. Modern
               computer systems are very good indeed at assuming they know what you want better than
               you do. Let’s never cease to doubt that, as Guy unquestionably did. Language and
               linguistic systems are not simple and data that purports to represent them are
               inherently and correspondingly complex. No single discipline knows all there is to
               know about it. We should respect that complexity, and seek to achieve comity in our
               trans-disciplinary investigations.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
