
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Welcome to the Jubilee </title>
    <author>Part Three : The Nineties</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>born digital</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-09-24">Created file</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>The 1990s: Things could only get better </head>
    <list rend="incremental">
     <item>Widespread discontent over the poll tax, mad cow disease, economic recession, and the
      resignation of several ministers finally brought down Mrs Thatcher. She was replaced by John
      Major, who did at least sign the Maastricht agreement which created the EU ... </item>
     <item> For years Belinda had in her window a sign saying “Stop the Poll Tax” and another saying
      “Free Nelson Mandela”, The first happened in 1992, the second in 1994. The sign saying “This
      is not here” didnt seem to have any effect. </item>
     <item> In academia, everyone was talking about something cool called the World Wide Web: I went
      to a conference in Warsaw in 1992 at which a French man assured a room full of skeptical
      hackers from across Europe that the Web would very soon be commercialised. The number of
      organisations with a Web presence went from a few hundred in 1990 to many thousands in 1999. </item>
     <item> On Mayday 1997, after 18 years of Tory misrule, the Labour party (well, Tony Blair) won
      a General Election with the biggest majority held by any government since 1935. </item>
     <item> In November 1994 Eurostar began services through the Channel Tunnel. </item>
     <item> The Good Friday Agreement was signed on 10th April 1998, bringing power sharing and at
      least the semblance of an end to Northern Ireland’s ‘Troubles’. </item>
     <item>This was the age of Brit Pop (Radiohead, Oasis, Blur, Pulp, Massive Attack, The Spice
      Girls ect ect ) </item>
    </list>
    <p>On the other hand: <list rend="incremental">
     <item>At the beginning of the year, we were suckered into joining the first Gulf War.</item>
     <item>In July 1998, a little bit of the British Empire called Hong Kong was handed back to the
      Chinese (it seemed a good idea at the time; it wasn't). </item>
     <item>Princess Diana died in a car crash at the end of august 1997, leading to widespread
      public lamentation and media frenzy. </item>
     </list></p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>1990: back to the future</head>
    <p>We started the new decade dancing the Lambada at Villa Caroline (those of us who can dance),
     but within a few days normal service was being resumed in chilly Walton Manor. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19900300_120007.jpg" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    <p>In February, there were floods in the University Parks and TEI geeks convened on Oxford for
     assorted meetings. And Elizabeth got some cool roller skates for her birthday</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19900200_119018.jpg" width="700px"/>
    </figure>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Travelling shoes</head>
    <p>In March, I started to build up my carbon foot print. The decade began with TEI meetings across
     the USA, and conferences across Europe. ... </p>
    <table rend="table">
     <row>
      <cell>8-10 March</cell>
      <cell>Chicago, IL</cell>
      <cell>Metalanguage Committee</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>12-14 March</cell>
      <cell>Tucson, AZ</cell>
      <cell>Analysis and Interpretation Committee</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>15-16 March</cell>
      <cell>Princeton, NJ</cell>
      <cell>Conference to launch Rutgers-Princeton Database project (later to become CETH)</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>17-18 March</cell>
      <cell>Bernardsville, NJ</cell>
      <cell>TEI Steering Committee</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>20 March</cell>
      <cell>Manhattan, NY</cell>
      <cell>Tourism with Antonio Zampolli</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>22-24 March</cell>
      <cell>Oxford (mirabile dictu)</cell>
      <cell>Text Documentation committee</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>2-5 April</cell>
      <cell>St Andrews</cell>
      <cell>Conference on Computers in Teaching</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>7 April</cell>
      <cell>Wolverhampton</cell>
      <cell>History and Computing Conferencec</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>25 April</cell>
      <cell>Sheffield</cell>
      <cell>IUSC Database Working Group</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>15-24 May</cell>
      <cell>Chicago, IL</cell>
      <cell>TEI editorial meeting</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>3-5 June</cell>
      <cell>Siegen, Germany</cell>
      <cell>ACH/ALLC Conference featuring first ever TEI Workshop</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>9-13 June</cell>
      <cell>Berlin</cell>
      <cell>ICAME corpus conference</cell>
     </row>
    </table>

    <p> Some say that the true meaning of "TEI" was "Travel Expenses Indefinitely". Certainly this
     sort of travelling became commonplace over the next few years; during the 90s, there were very,
     very, few months during which I was not attending a meeting, conference, or workshop somewhere
     in the US or Europe, or other more exotic locations in the far east.  But these were not family occasions, so I won't detail them
     further.</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19920305_000000.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>Rare action shot of me giving a talk about the TEI, some time in March 1992. Note suit
      and tie and OHP.</head>
    </figure>

   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Tradition! Tradition! </head>
    <p>Girls' birthdays were increasingly endowed with elaborate Tata-produced cakes: another fine
     tradition. </p>
    <table rend="table">
     <row>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19900300_120022.jpg" width="500px"/>
       <head>April 1990: a burger for Sarah</head>
       </figure></cell>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19910402_000002.png" width="500px"/>
       <head>April 1991: a tropical island for Sarah</head>
       </figure></cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19940217_000001.png" width="500px"/>
       <head>February 1994: a cheque book for Elizabeth</head>
       </figure></cell>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19940402_000002.png" width="500px"/>
       <head>April 1994: more naked ladies for Sarah</head>
       </figure></cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19960217_000001.png" width="500px"/>
       <head>February 1996: a teddy bears picnic for Elizabeth</head>
       </figure></cell>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19981100_000001.jpg" width="500px"/>
       <head>November 1998: a reprised chocolate house for Belinda</head>
       </figure></cell>
     </row>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Graduations</head>
    <p>This was also the decade in which (nearly) everyone got certificated at some sort of
     graduation ceremony... </p>
    <table>
     <row>
      <cell>In June 1992, Lilette graduated from the OU at Brighton</cell>
      <cell><graphic url="../media/19920600_000002.jpg" width="600px"/></cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell><graphic url="../media/19960600_000005.jpg" width="600px"/></cell>
      <cell>In June 1996, Belinda graduated from Nottingham</cell>
     </row>
     <row>
      <cell>In July 1997, Sarah graduated from De Montfort</cell>
      <cell>><graphic url="../media/19990700_142009.jpg" width="600px"/></cell>
     </row>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Lodgers</head>
    <p>The top floor of no 110 had two bedrooms, one of which we split in two. For most of the year
     there was a steady flow of student lodgers sleeping there, usually eating dinner with us, and
     always helping to keep the mortgage under some degree of control.
     <!--(Though borrowing money to do
     more repair work on the house was never a problem: this being the start of a time in which
     property values in Oxford progressed from absurd to beyond ridiculous.)--></p>
    <p>The lodgers were not university students, but a mixture of A-level re-takers, lost souls
     striving to scrape through entrance exams, abandoned children of expat poshos from across the
     world. A few became family friends, but only a few. The Japanese were the most polite and they
     always came bearing gifts. </p>
    <table>
     <row>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19941031_000000.jpg" width="400px"/>
       <head>Halloween 1994</head>
       </figure> </cell>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/20110300_000001_visitor.jpg" width="600px"/>
       </figure></cell>
     </row>
    </table>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Performances </head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19901012_000003.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>Belinda and Rob shared a pineapple in Cherwell School's fine production of <hi>Cabaret</hi>
      (September 1990)</head>
    </figure>

    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19910000_000001.png" width="600px"/>
     <head>Sarah sang jazz numbers in trendy Oxford cafes whenever she could find a pianist (here,
      the Dome in October 1991)</head>
    </figure>

    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19920700_000003.png" width="600px"/>
     <head>As a change from endless tours of <hi>Dido</hi>, the Oxford Girls Choir also gave us Roddy Williams'
      take on <hi>Alice in Wonderland</hi> in July 1992</head>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19940400_000001.png" height="600px"/>
     <head>In April 1994, one of Sarah's admirers gave her this remarkable music stand as a birthday present</head>
    </figure>
    
</div><div type="slide"><head>West End performances</head>
    <p>In June 1993, everyone had a role with the Mushy Pea Theatre Company, culminating in
     performances of <hi>Babes</hi> and <hi>Mr Majeika</hi> at the Shaw Theatre in London</p>
    <table>
     <row>
      <cell> <figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19930600_000002.png" height="600px"/>
       <head>Semi-pro musicians going to (or maybe returning from) London baby, London.</head>
       </figure></cell>
      <cell> <figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19930605_000001.png" width="600px"/>
       <head>Sarah starred as Wilhelmina Worlock in <title>Mr Majeika</title></head>
       </figure> </cell>
     </row>
    </table>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Teenager in the house</head>
    <table>
     <row>
      <cell><figure>
       <graphic url="../media/19960200_000001.png" width="600px"/>
       <head>Elizabeth and her posse on the street, 1996</head>
       </figure></cell>
      <cell><graphic url="../media/erb-friends.png" width="500px"/></cell>
     </row>
    </table>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Holidays</head>
    <p>I wasn't the only person travelling in the nineties. There were also holiday expeditions
     involving current boyfriends, separate expeditions not involving parents, or not involving me,
     as well as grand community escapades. For example: 
    </p><p>In August 1994, we rented a holiday villa in Crete and did summer holiday things like this</p>
    <table>
     <row>
     
      <cell><figure><graphic url="../media/19940800_000030.jpg" width="500px"/><head>Here
       we are with Sir Arthur Evans in Knossos</head></figure></cell><cell>
       <figure><graphic url="../media/19940500_000001.png" width="500px"/><head>Synchronized swimming in the hotel pool, sort of</head></figure></cell>
     </row></table>
    <p>In March 1997, we organized a mass expedition to the Trattorio da Olga in Cereglio, just over the hill from Guy's house in Liserna. This was to celebrate Guy's 50th (and
     mine and Lilette's too), though we returned frequently thereafter, on any excuse. </p>
    <table> <row>
      <cell><graphic url="../media/19970323_000000.jpg" width="650px"/></cell>
     <cell><graphic url="../media/19970323_000003.jpg" width="600px"/></cell>
     </row></table>
    <p>In July 1998, everyone went to Mauritius, without me (I stayed in Oxford to run the
     first ever Text Encoding Summer School, closely followed by TALC conference)</p>
     <figure>
      <graphic url="../media/19980700_146023.png" width="700px"/>
     </figure>
    <p>And in August 1999, at Allen Renear's invitation, we took Elizabeth on her first transatlantic adventure, via Iceland. We  explored Boston, Providence, and Newport RI. We also had a few days cat-sitting in Greenwich Village  and visited MOMA. </p>
    <table> <row>
     <cell><graphic url="../media/19990817_141001.jpg" height="500px"/></cell>
      <cell><graphic url="../media/19990800_136012.jpg" width="500px"/></cell>
     </row>
    </table>
   </div><div type="slide"><head>Moving on</head>
   <p>In September 1999, Belinda moved out of student accomodation in Forest Fields and into somewhere just a bit posher, with Bob.
   <figure><graphic url="../media/19990900_141026.png" width="600px"/></figure>
  </p><p>Around the same time, Sarah  moved out of Forest Fields to London, with Angus. </p><p>.... but you'll have to wait for the next decade to see what happened next. </p></div>
   
   
  </body>
 </text>

</TEI>
