
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Welcome to the Jubilee </title>
    <author>Part Two : The Eighties</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>born digital</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-10-02">Created file</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>1980s : a mixed decade</head>
    <list rend="incremental">
     <item>Mrs Thatcher, the Iron Lady, was in charge most of the time. So, still not a
      <emph>great</emph> time to be in England...<list rend="incremental">
      <item>In 1982, we went to war with Argentina, over the Falklands. We won, for a change. </item>
      <item>The Miners' strike of 1984 turned into a confrontation between government and unions;
       the government won. </item>
      <item>In Ireland, the "Troubles" continued, with bombings, assassinations, and hunger strikes
       ...</item>
      <item>The Thatcher government continued to shrink the state and privatise everything in
       sight</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>It wasn't all bad <list rend="incremental">
      <item>The Rubik's Cube first appeared, as did Pac-Man, Super Mario, and Donkey Kong</item>
      <item>IT spread out of the workplace into the home with a rash of "personal computers" : the
       IBM PC (1981); the Macintosh (1984); the Commodore 64 ; the BBC micro; the Amiga... </item>
      <item>MTV was launched in the UK; also The Simpsons.</item>
      <item>In 1981, Prince Charles and Lady Diana were married and everyone had a day off to
       watch</item>
      <item>The World Wide Web was (allegedly) invented in 1989</item>
      <item>The Berlin Wall fell and the Cold War started to thaw, kind of</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>We were property owners and I had a good job with proper pension rights!</item>
    </list>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Saturday morning shopping</head>

    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19800300_094007.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>Woolworth's pick n' mix</head>
    </figure>

    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19800300_000001.jpg" width="500px"/>
    </figure>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Tradition!</head>

    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19800400_078027.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>2 April 1980 : chocolate cake remains popular</head>
    </figure>
   
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19801225_000002.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>25 Dec 1980 : Christmas Dinner </head>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19810900_091004.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>September 1981 : we went blackberrying </head>
    </figure>
  <!--  <p>I had half of an over-grown allotment, which was also surrounded with brambles, accessible by disused railway line. </p>
  -->  
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Home Improvements</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19800600_000000.jpg" height="700px"/>
    </figure>

    <cb/>
    <list rend="incremental">
     <item>At this date, mortgage debt was also popular. </item>
     <item>We lived in Plantation Road long enough, and my credit was good enough, for us to
      undertake various home improvements, like installing central heating (on George's
      recommendation), enlarging the kitchen, and adding a balcony at the back. </item>
     <item>This is the back of the house at the start of the update process in June 1980 </item>
     <item>When works were completed, we gave a very good party for the builders, a local outfit led
      by Andy Wrigley. </item>
    </list>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>French Holiday adventures</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19800800_000001.jpg" height="700px"/>
     <head>Pam is the only one still cheerful by the time we got to the Gare du Nord</head>
    </figure>
    <cb/>
    <list rend="incremental">
     <item>In August 1980, we took Pam with us on what should have been a simple expedition to
      Cherbourg by boat and train. </item>
     <item>Striking French fishermen complicated things by blockading the channel ports, so we
      travelled via Dover and Zeebrugge, Calais, and Paris instead, taking two days and nights, and
      making considerable use of my Flexible Friend. </item>
     <item>(Remember that this was all in a distant age before the channel tunnel, before Eurostar,
      before cashpoints, before the euro) </item>
     <item>But when we eventually got to our seaside bungalow near Barneville, the beaches,
      sunshine, sand dunes, French food were all just wonderful. </item>
    </list>
   </div>
<div type="slide"><head>A veddink</head>
<p>Also wonderful, in its own way, was Grandma's wedding for which the girls got new pink dresses and lots of elderly relatives appeared. It was catered by a rather nice hotel in Windsor, and was my first encounter with beef wellington. </p>
 <figure>
  <graphic url="../media/19810105_000003.jpg" width="750px"/>
  <head>5 Jan 1981</head>
 </figure>


</div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>1982</head>
    <p>After a few years, we decided we had outgrown the house and were ready to move on. In April,
     Belinda and Sarah were given the opportunity to redecorate our bedroom wall : </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19820400_000002.jpg" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    <p>In unrelated news, not content with innumerable swimming certificates and such like, Belinda
     started learning to play the violin. <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19820900_000000.jpg" width="500px"/>
     <head>Sounding quite good, by September</head>
     </figure></p>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Swanage</head>
    <p>The same year, in August, we went on a proper family seaside holiday</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19820700_000002.jpg" width="450px"/>
    </figure>
    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19820700_000001.jpg" width="400px"/>
    </figure>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Financial wizardry</head>
    <p>In 1982, we sold Plantation Road for £24,000. But moving on still required a new mortgage: I
     made it big enough to finance a holiday trip to Malawi as well. So we spent Christmas 1982
     visiting friends and family in Limbe, Blantyre, and Zomba again. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19821219_36X225.jpg" width="700px"/>
     <head>Chez Alain, 10 Dec 1982</head>
    </figure>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Onward to Walton Manor, March 1983 </head>
    <list>
     <item> Fresh new mortgage in hand we moved decisively up the property ladder and into proper
      North Oxford, or Walton Manor at least. </item>
     <item>Our new address, 110 Southmoor Rd, was a magnificent four storey victorian mansion, a
      snip at £53,000. It had been minimally improved by the vendors, but was in need of constant
      repair, which (in due course) we gave it.</item>
     <item>We moved in on 25 March 1983, and stayed there (eventually) for the next 30 years.</item>
    </list>
    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/110-southmoor.png" width="500px"/>
     <head>110 is the slightly grubbier one on the left. </head>
    </figure>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Hello Elizabeth!</head>

   <table><row><cell> <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/erbAuto-1.png" width="500px"/>
     <head>(From ERB's 1990 autobiography) </head>
    </figure>
</cell><cell>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19840200_103021.jpg" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
  </cell></row></table>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Life in the 80s</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19831022_000001.jpg" height="600px"/>
     <head>In October 1983, the Woodcraft Folk (West Oxford Branch) went to London to do their bit for CND.</head>
    </figure>
    
    
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19840700_159022.jpg" height="600px"/>
     <head>Grandma gave us this hand-made depiction of Burnard Towers to celebrate our fifth year
      there/</head>
    </figure>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19850700_153023.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>In July 1985, we went for a bracing Cornish holiday, taking in St Michael's Mount. It
      didn't rain ALL the time, but Lilette vowed she would never visit the English seaside
      again.</head>
    </figure>

   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Celebrations</head>
    <list>
     <item>Inter alia, there were school fetes and the Little Clarendon St Fair and the Jericho
      Festival.. </item>
     <item>In June 1986, there was a special street party to celebrate our street's hundredth
      birthday (or thereabouts).</item>
     <item>I concocted and distributed a register of the inhabitants from old street directories.
      Belinda played in a scratch orchestra. There was tea and cake, and face painting, and
      bagpipes. Very North Oxford.</item>
    </list>
    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19860622_000000.png" width="600px"/>
     <head> Colin Matthew piped in the event</head>
    </figure>
   </div>


   <div type="slide">
    <head>1987</head>
    <list>
     <item>Belinda starred as Tevye in Cherwell School's 1987 production of <title>Fiddler on the
      Roof</title> (little knowing ...) <figure>
      <graphic url="../media/19870400_000001.jpg" width="650px"/>
      </figure></item>
     <item>Sarah and the rest of the Oxford Girls Choir took Dido on tour in France in August</item>
     <item>Lilette celebrated her birthday at an OU summer school in Scotland </item>
     <item>In September I took up a month-long fellowship in Gottingen at the Max Planck Institute
      for Historical Research (sounds better in German)</item>

     <item>And then... </item>
    </list>
   </div>


   <div type="slide">
    <head>Birth of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) </head>
    <p>(I'll give my lecture on the global significance of the TEI another day) </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19871111_000000.jpg" width="700px"/>
     <head>Encoding weirdos convene: Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, 12 Nov 1987 </head>
    </figure>
    <p>Possibly the first time I'd been unavoidably absent for Belinda's birthday. But not the last. </p>

   </div>




   <div type="slide">
    <head>April 1988</head>
  <table><row> <cell> <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19880400_000001.jpg" width="500px"/>
     <head>Saturday morning in Selfridges</head>
    </figure></cell><cell>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19880000_queensmc.png" width="500px"/>
     <head>I somehow blagged a job at BP and this is the computer the queen lent me to do it
      on.</head>
    </figure></cell></row></table>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>In 1988, Pam and Mike got married at Wolfson College</head>
   <table><row><cell> <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19881001_000001.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head> Smart dressing obligatory</head>
    </figure>
    </cell><cell>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19881001_000002.png" width="500px"/>
     <head>1 October 1988</head>
    </figure></cell></row></table>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>April 1989</head>
   <table><row><cell> <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19890400-poster.png" height="600px"/>
    </figure>
    </cell><cell>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19890400_092009.jpg" width="700px"/>
     <head>The 80s were also famous for costume drama</head>
    </figure></cell></row></table>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>But we finished the decade by taking another tropical Xmas holiday</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19891200_000002.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>Grandmère made us a cake</head>
    </figure>
    <p>This time, we all went to Mauritius to visit grandmère in Curepipe, with side trips to Villa
     Caroline to see in new year, to Port Louis and its Grapefruit Gardens, to various Mauritian parties
     ... </p>
    <p> <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19891200_173017.jpg" width="700px"/>
     <head>Curepipe Botanical Gardens</head>
     </figure></p>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>

 <!-- 1990
  dancing the lambada
  
	-->
</TEI>
