
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Welcome to the Jubilee </title>
    <author>Part One : The Seventies</author>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>born digital</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-09-24">Created file</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>1972 </head>
    <list rend="incremental">
     <item>Not a <emph>great</emph> time to be in England...<list rend="incremental">
      <item>Drastic energy shortages led to the "three day week" in the winter of 1973 and a state of
       emergency; miners and dockers went on strike.</item>
      <item>A Tory Chancellor cut taxes: inflation soared; the pound was devalued; unemployment
       soared... sound familiar?</item>
      <item>In Ireland, following Bloody Sunday, IRA bombing campaigns began; the "Troubles"
       ...</item>
      <item>Idi Amin, president of Uganda, expelled thousands of Asians to the UK, many of whom
       opened corner shops and thus revived the British economy</item>
      <item>Second "Cod war" with Iceland (we lost)</item>
      <item>Watergate scandal in the U.S. leading eventually to President Nixon's resignation</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>It wasn't all bad <list rend="incremental">
      <item>We joined the Common Market in January 1972 (no-one noticed)</item>
      <item>General discontent eventually brought down Heath's Tory government</item>
      <item>Jesus Christ Superstar opened in the West End; Emmerdale Farm started on ITV</item>
      <item>The New Seekers nearly won Eurovision (they came second, after Luxembourg's Vicky
       Leandros) </item>
      <item>Your flexible friend the Access credit card first appeared</item>
      </list></item>
     <item>Fortunately, we were in Africa</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>... Malawi! where it all started ... </head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19721200.jpg" height="70%"/>
    </figure>
    <list>
     <item>December 1972 : a serendipitous double exposure</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>It was just a simple Mauritian wedding</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19721223_invite.png" width="650px"/>
    </figure>
    
    <cb/>

    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19721223_mothers.png" width="600px"/>
     <head>23 December 1972 : Limbe Cathedral</head> </figure>
   
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>I don't remember much about the party</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19721223_marbella.png" width="700px"/>
    </figure>
    <list>
     <item>There was an appropriate amount of dancing and eating</item>
     <item>And Guy made a speech</item>
     <item>But sadly, most photos of the event are lost (there were goat balls)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <!--<div type="slide">
    <head>And before long...</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19730527.jpg" width="60%" height="60%"/>
    </figure>
    <cb/>
    <p> We lived in this
     block of expat flats, next to the Kamuzu Stadium in Limbe, until the university moved to a new
     site in Zomba.</p>
    <p><graphic url="../media/19720500_ferrograph.jpg" height="10%" width="20%"/> I spent some time
     teaching, and some time doing a late night radio show on MBC. And writing letters and making
     audio tapes. </p>
    <p>Lilette had secretarial work at Blantyre Print and Publishing until her Condition made this
     infeasible. </p>
   </div>-->

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Jan 1972 - Dec 1973 </head>
    <p>My first real academic job was as Lecturer in English, at a newly-established University in
     the equally newly-established country of Malawi. To be honest, I didn't apply for a job here; I
     applied for one in Fiji, but whatever remnant of empire was responsible for recruiting to
     commonwealth universities offered me this one instead. It was tropical, it was a job. I took
     it. </p>
    <p>With the job came my first proper flat and my first car, and indeed my first personal servant
     unless you count Oxford scouts. His name was Jim Kandiado and he looked after me, and (in due
     course) Lilette very well. </p>
    <p>The flat was on the ground floor of a modern block, just over the road from the Kamuzu
     Stadium, on the Makata road. and it looked like this: <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19720000_chichiri.png" width="600px"/>
     </figure></p>
    <p>I lived here for an eventful year, coming to terms with the strangeness of being a
     <foreign>mzungu</foreign>, and an academic to boot. The beautiful Mauritian girl who moved in
     with me helped a lot. After a year the University moved to Zomba, and so therefore did we. This
     photo shows the huge University lorry which came to move us:</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/1973-chichiri-movingout-03019.jpg" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    <p>Our new home was much more traditional. In fact, I dont even think it had an address. It was
     one of a small number of European Bungalows built along the Old Naisi Road in the days when the
     Colonial Government occupied Zomba. With independence, the government had moved to somewhere
     else, leaving behind some rather fine antique housing stock for expats like me and my fellow
     academics to snap up. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/1973-chilwa-04021.jpg" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    <p>From the garden of our bungalow (which had all sorts of fruit trees) you could see Lake
     Chirwa on a clear day. There was a village built of mud huts within walking distance and wild
     pigs in the surrounding gardens. I learned how to to drive around the Zomba plateau at
     dangerous speeds so as to get to the Zomba Gymkhana Club in time for the ham sandwich which
     Lilette was inexplicably craving. Belinda was born here. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Hello Belinda!</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19731111_belinda.jpg" width="700px"/>
    </figure>
    <list>
     <item>Zomba, 11 Nov 1973</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>1974: Back to Europe</head>
    <p>We delayed as long as possible the business of finding a post-Malawian residence by visiting
     friends and families on an extended European tour, courtesy of the flexible air ticket which I
     got as a returning expat. Belinda was not entirely enthusiastic but she had no choice. </p>

    <p>From Malawi, we went via Lusaka in Zambia to Rome and then to Bologna where we saw the New
     Year in with Guy's commie chums (in those days the Italian communist party was very middle
     class)</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19740101.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>Bologna, 1 Jan 1974</head>
    </figure>
    <p>Then we proceeded to Paris and to Caen to introduce Tata Nicole and Tonton Jef to Belinda
     (and vice versa) </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19740100_caen.jpg" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    <p>And finally, I drove a hire car through the darkness to Hamilton Road, Oxford (thanks for the
     floor, Pam) and thence to my mum's flat in Bristol, where we crashed for a bit </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19740200_bristol.png" width="650px"/>
    </figure>
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>12 Harefields</head>
    <p>Eventually we settled down in a rented modern house in Harefields, in the unfashionably far
     North of Oxford. It looked like this:</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19740300_harefields.jpg" height="600px"/>
     <head>This was our first family home. Belinda learned to walk first up and then down the stairs
      (of which there were many) and we joined baby-sitting circles and started doing things like
      Sunday outings. </head>
    </figure>

    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19740300_park.jpg" height="600px"/>
     
     <head>Healthy walk in Cutteslowe Park, March 1974. Belinda snoozes.</head>
    </figure>
    
    <p> Lilette did a lot of pram pushing and home building, and some shopping.</p>
    <p>In April I got a job at the University's computing service: not a very demanding one, but it
     paid the rent, and left me ample time to think about other things. </p>

   </div>
   
   
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Cutteslowe life</head>

    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19740400_afro.jpg" width="600px"/>
     
     <head>Waiting for the bus in Cornmarket, April 1974. Belinda continues to snooze</head>
    </figure>
   </div>
   <!-- june 1975 we went to Cherbourg via Air Aurigny -->
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Some traditions started...</head>
    <p></p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19741200_000000.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>December 1974 and Grandma visits to honour our first traditional Christmas tree</head>
    </figure>
    
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19751110_000004.jpg" width="600px"/>
     <head>Belinda's lifelong fascination with chocolate cake probably dates back to her second
      birthday in 1975</head>
    </figure>
    </div>
   
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Hello Sarah Daisy!</head>
    <p>New baby in the house (much more interesting than Present, the cat)</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19760406.jpg"/>
     <!-- 494 x 674 -->
     <head>Sarah Daisy arrived (just in time to make a difference to my tax return) 2 April
      1976</head>
    </figure>
 
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>18 Plantation Rd</head>
    <list rend="incremental">
     <!--<item>In those distant days, if you wanted to get a loan to buy your own home, you needed to
      earn enough to be able to pay a hefty cash deposit, plus all manner of additional conditions
      and restrictions. But we still wanted to stop paying the landlord's mortgage, and start paying
      our own, and so I invested a lot of effort in calculations and arguments with banks, which
      eventually paid off</item>-->
     <item>In the spring of 1977 we became property owners, courtesy of the Halifax Building
      Society. We paid £7000 for 18 Plantation Rd, a little house in North Oxford which St Johns
      College had decided it wasn't worth their while keeping since one of its exterior walls was
      bowed, and it needed modernisation, and it had squatters. </item>
     <item>We hired a local builder called Mr Wastie to set about rectifying the most pressing
      defects (a huge bolt was fixed into the bowed wall, the nice wooden partitions upstairs were
      covered by boring but comparatively fireproof plaster board, we installed a bathroom with a
      real bath in it, and so on: total cost about £5000 I think). </item>
     <item>The squatters were not a problem: indeed they left us a nice welcome message scrawled in
      charcoal on the wall.</item>
     <item> And thus we moved up the property ladder, and into Central North Oxford, on the fringes
      of Jericho. Its front looked much the same then as it does now...</item>
    </list>
    <cb/>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/18-plantation-rd_streetview.png" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    
    
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>Jericho life in the 70s</head>
    <p>To cope with the winter. Lilette made some theatrical velvet curtains to keep
     out the draughts. </p>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/19760000_curtains.png" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    <p>Belinda and Sarah went to St Barnabas and made lots of friends.</p>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/19781000_000000.png" width="600px"/>
    <head>Joanna, Belinda, Charlotte, Martha, and Sarah. Definitely not posing on our foamy sofa.</head></figure>
    <p> We drank in the Victoria occasionally, and the Gardeners more frequently, especially at Sunday lunch time. And there were plenty of festivities and street fairs marking the passage of time.</p>
  
     
   </div>
   
   

   <div type="slide">
    <head>1977 : Travelling</head>
    <p>In August, I got funding to attend an International Summer School on Computational
     Linguistics in Pisa. </p>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/19770800_pisa.jpg" height="600px"/><head>A rare early sighting of me in a conference suit and tie</head></figure>
    
    <p>This gave us an excuse to swop houses with a friend of Guy's who had a villa in Florence, and
     also to introduce the girls to Vergato. </p>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/19770800_vergato.jpg" width="600px"/></figure>
    <p>Aloysius liked it so much he stayed there and had to be returned by post. </p>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/19770900_teddy.png" width="600px"/></figure>
   </div>

   <div type="slide"><head>Visitors</head>
    <p>February 1978: Despite the snow, Pam baby-sat so that we could run away to Paris for a few days child-free.
     <figure><graphic url="../media/19780200-pam.png" width="600px"/></figure>
    </p>
    
    <p>August 1978: Grandmère Toussaint visited </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="../media/19780800_000000.png" width="600px"/>
    </figure>
    
    
   </div>

   <div type="slide">
    <head>1979 : Hols, and how</head>
    <p>By the end of the decade, we were a much travelled lot. In  1979 we took three family holidays: </p>
    <list>
     <item>In April, we stayed at Viv's house on the Isle of Wight </item>
     <item>In May, we went to see Jef, Nicole and all the Lebranchus <emph>en masse</emph> in France </item>
     <item>In September we went to the Italian seaside for a change, end-of-season Rimini</item>
    </list>
    <p>Sarah's chin had a dramatic accident in Bologna: </p>
    <cb/>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/1980-sarahChin.png" width="500px"/></figure>
   </div>
   <div type="slide">
    <head>Ready for a new decade</head>
    <p>Our policy of continuous home improvement resulted in some new kitchen cupboards, to celebrate which I suggested moustaches all round.</p>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/19791000_000002.jpg" width="600px"/>
    <head>(Sarah's chin had recovered by October)</head></figure>
    
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
 <!-- 1980 
  06 building extension
  08: to cherbourg (eventually) via Belgium
  1982-09 B starts violin
  1982 -3 : to Malawi
  1983-03-25 move to southmoor rd
  1984-02-17 : elizabeth born
  1986-06-22: Smoor rd centenary partry
  1987-11-12 Poughkeepsie
  1988-10-01 : pam got married again
  1989-04 : dido and aeneas
  1989-03-23 : the non centenary at liserna; also gordon at colognole
	returning to b*b
	1989-12 : to mauritius. Curepipe; villa caroline; flicenfklac
	-->
 <!-- 1990
  dancing the lambada
  
	-->
</TEI>
