<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes towards a definition of TEI Conformance</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Made up from thin air</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-03-16">Revised following CMSCQ's comments on blog version</change>
         <change when="2017-03-14">First draft</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div rend="slide">
            <head>What is TEI conformance? </head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <graphic url="media/oddflavours.png"/>
               </figure></p>
            <p>Each of the blobs here represents three subtly different things: <list>
                  <item>an ODD : that is, a collection of TEI specifications</item>
                  <item>a formal schema generated from that ODD, and its natural language
                     documentation</item>
                  <item>the set of documents considered valid by that schema</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>The TEI provides TEI All : a set of over 500 uniquely identifiable elements, classes,
               attributes, etc. and a schema in which they are all permitted. For all practical
               purposes a user of the TEI must make a selection from this cornucopia, and we call
               that selection a <term>TEI subset</term>. Of course there are many many possible TEI
               subsets, each making different choices of elements or attributes or classes, but the
               sets of documents which each consequent schema will validate all have in common that
               they will also be considered valid by the schema TEI All. </p>
            <p>A user of the TEI may however do more than simply choose a subset of the provided
               specifications. They may also provide additional constraints for aspects of an
               encoding left underspecified by the TEI, for example by requiring that attribute
               values be taken from a closed list of possible values rather than being any
               syntactically valid token. They may simply change the datatype of an attribute, for
               example from a string to an integer or a date. They may also provide an alternative
               identifier for an element or an attribute, for example to change its canonical
               English name for one from another language. In some cases, attribute value changes
               are equivalent to a subsetting operation; in others not. Renaming operations never
               result in a subset: a document in which the element names have all been changed to
               their French equivalents cannot be validated by an English language version of TEI
               All. A user of the TEI can also change the content model or the class membership of
               existing TEI elements, in ways which may or may not be equivalent to a subsetting
               operation.</p>
            <p> We use the term <term>customised subset</term> for all these kinds of
               personalisation because they result in something which is not necessarily a further
               subset of the TEI subset concerned, but a further modification of it. In the general
               case, their conformance with TEI All can be determined only by inspection, and their
               validation may require some additional processing.</p>
            <p>Finally, a user of the TEI is at liberty to define entirely new elements and
               attributes, and to make such components members of existing TEI classes so that
               existing TEI elements may refer to them. They may also modify the content models of
               existing TEI elements to refer explicitly to such new elements. This results in an
                  <term>extended subset</term>, since it contains elements or attributes additional
               to those provided by the TEI All schema. Such additional components should always be
               labelled as belonging to a non-TEI namespace. A processor can then determine that
               these components may be left out of consideration when determining the validity of a
               document with respect to TEI All.</p>
            <p>In additional to these formal considerations, TEI conformance involves attention to
               some less easily verifiable constraints, specifically the twin requirements of
                  <term>honesty</term> and <term>explicitness</term>. By honesty we mean that
               elements in the TEI namespace must respect the semantics which the TEI Guidelines
               supply as a part of their definition. By explicitness we mean that all modifications
               (i.e. both customized and extended subsets) should be expressed using an ODD to
               document exactly how the TEI declarations on which they are based have been derived.
               (An ODD need not of course be based on the TEI at all, but in that case the question
               of TEI conformance does not arise)</p>
            <p>Formally speaking, we can say of a document that it is TEI conformant if : <list>
                  <item>it is a well formed XML document; and </item>
                  <item>it is valid against the TEI All schema :
                     <list>
                        <item>without modification (it is a TEI subset), or </item>
                        <item>after deletion of any elements it contains which are not in the TEI namespace including
                           their children, irrespective of namespace (it is a TEI extension), or </item>
                        <item>after application of any canonicalization algorithm specified by its associated
                           ODD (it is a TEI customized subset)
                        </item>
                     </list></item><item>its usage of TEI elements respects the intended function of those
                        elements as defined by the TEI Guidelines</item><item>its usage of the TEI markup scheme is
                           documented by a TEI-conformant  ODD or analogous documentation
                     </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>The purpose of these rules is to make interchange of documents easier. They do not
               however guarantee it, and they certainly do not provide any guarantee of
               interoperability. Unlike many other standards, the goal of the TEI is not enforce
               consistency of encoding, but to provide a means by which encoding choices and
               policies may be more readily understood, and hence (to some extent) algorithmically
               comparable.</p>
         </div>
        
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
