<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Travels with Guy</title>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2018-12-06T15:53:52.959770923</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>no publication statement available</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Tidied up versions of Guy's facebook postings</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <name>Lou</name>
               <date>2018-12-06T18:03:09.783319405</date>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Liserna-Malaga-Liserna January/Febrary 2015</head>
            <div n="1">
               <head> 2015-01-25</head>
               <p>And it's off we go. 1st class to Turin after lunch with Fabrizio and Cristina, who
                  convey their wonderful sense of deja vu as they prepare for their third daughters'
                  wedding (well, third wedding, second oldest daughter, to be exact). Camilla and
                  Giovanni left to construct and fill cardboard boxes with Daniela's infinite
                  accumulations to be transported into the hills. After Friday's earthquake shook
                  Liserna, the main themes of this trip were fixed yesterday evening when I booked
                  tickets for two visits to the Prado, to see their two Brueg(h)els - The Wine of St
                  Martin, and The Triumph of Death. Both large and vastly detailed works, each with
                  hundreds of figures, each meriting hours of study. On the death theme (hereafter
                  M=mors), I then caught Verdi's Requiem on BBC radio; on the wine theme (hereafter
                  V=vin) I dropped into Francesca's - my longstanding Tuscan-speaking supplier of
                  Tuscan plonque in the village - this morning, and ordered five dozen bottles for
                  delivery on my return. Seemed appropriate. Now a beautiful clear day as we cross
                  the Po, and the Freccia Rossa wifi has allowed me to download suitable reading
                  matter for the trip - Cervantes, what else, Alan? What could this sterile,
                  illtilled wit of mine beget but the story of a dry, shrivelled, whimsical
                  offspring? But no windmills to be seen (yet) in the Po valley. </p>
               <p>Just a beautiful clear afternoon observing snow-covered Alps along with a
                  beautiful young lady from Barcelona, doing a PhD in Lyons on medical imaging. Our
                  ways parted in Turin where she was getting the bus to Lyon, and I had an hour to
                  wait in for the train to Bardonecchia, in honour of the forecast for which (-9°C)
                  woolly socks were dutifully shod. Spent discussing smartphone offers with messrs
                  TIM, amazingly open on Sunday afternoon, and looking at books in Feltrinelli
                  (idem). If I ever do this again it'll have to have pictures, ie a new phone.</p>
               <quote>CHAPTER I. WHICH TREATS OF THE CHARACTER AND PURSUITS OF THE FAMOUS GENTLEMAN DON
                  QUIXOTE OF LA MANCHA</quote>
               <p>The last time I spent a night in Bardonecchia was two years ago (in a different
                  hostelry), with Daniela on the way to Chambery. The food was terrible, the wine
                  worse. Nothing has changed other than D's absence, further not helped by the fact
                  that what Fabrizio and Cristina gave me for lunch today was an identical menu
                  (albeit better cooked) to that of the San Francesco Convent dinner this evening -
                  spaghetti, chicken, and roast potatoes. Yet more deja vu. F+C's red wine was
                  rather better too. I have persuaded the manager to turn the heating on, and so to
                  bed. None nuns in sight on site.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
               <head>2015-01-26</head>
               <p>I'd forgotten how splendid the snow-covered jagged rocky Alps coming down from
                  Modane can be. To Chambery at 1030 on a Monday morning is dead, everything shut
                  bar the Maison de Savoie, which runs to a mediocre coffee and croissant. A stroll
                  along familiar streets up to the Elephants, also shut under restoration but
                  covered wwith lifesize pictures of their bottoms: "pour la première fois nous le
                  montre". And nothing really happens all day - Valence TGV stations hardly counts
                  as an event at any stretch of imagination. Cervantes evokes chivalry: a lady drops
                  her hat unnoticedly while getting off the train to Valence, so I shout to attract
                  attention and throw it out of the door after her as it closes. That's it A
                  half-hour delay before Montpellier, so pitch dark as we hit the very noisy tunnel
                  under the frontier at 260km/h. Not an eventful day. Chambery just reminded me of
                  last time (sob). A half bottle of Sauvignon from the Chambery Casino slowly
                  vanishes at seat 126 of coach 1 on the double-decker TGV (recommended choice).
                  Coming into Barcellona Sants at 9pm, it's time for</p>
               <quote>CHAPTER XVI. OF WHAT HAPPENED TO THE INGENIOUS GENTLEMAN IN THE INN WHICH HE TOOK
                  TO BE A CASTLE</quote>
               <p>- not Castillian, presumably Catalan. Took me half an hour to find it. And another
                  half hour to find a Spanish plug. Tomorrow, lunch in San Cugat with Grazia's
                  husband Bruno, if I can find any of the three.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
               <head>2015-01-27</head>
               <p>Day 3 began with Coffee and croissant in the bar up by Plaza Espanya, and
                  proceeded with two hours work refining(?) my paper for Malaga before ... heading
                  for San Cugat. Barcelona reminds me of Mexico City; intense suburbs and then a
                  green belt of tree-covered hillsides, only they haven't had to build walls here to
                  stop unauthorised building further up the hills. Bruno is splendid: now in his
                  mid-eighties, he tells me his life story, a child in Eritrea during the fascist
                  empire, emigrated from Italy to Barcelona, set up what is now the only factory
                  producing offset printing plates in Spain (with a subsidiary in China), married
                  Daniela's friend MariaGrazia ... and buys me a fishy lunch in an old farmhouse
                  next to the motorway. A good lunch, and good insonorisation to boot. Then I get a
                  tour of the factory, and meet their son Lorenzo, who now more or less runs the
                  firm. I am amazed by the staff uniforms - not just the manual workers, but also
                  the office staff. Bruno tells me the latter have two (different) uniforms for each
                  of the four seasons. This week it's all in red woolies. I more or less understand
                  the technology, thanks to my Methuen Educational background, less the
                  psychology.</p>
               <p>A triumph of ticketing: I purchased what turned out (my Catalan is restricted:
                  does viatje = journeys or journeypersons?) to be a single ticket for two people to
                  San Cugat (or that's what's printed on the ticket), not a two-journey ticket for
                  one as I hoped. But I try using it as a return for one person, and receive no
                  objections from the four various machineries encountered. Isn't that nice!</p>
               <p>But I'm leaving Barcelona, clearly too soon. This evening I just found the local
                  covered market as it was closing, and what looked like the ideal bar for
                  breakfast, conveniently placed on the way to Estacio Sants. Hope to be there by
                  7.30 tomorrow morning - it reminded me of Covent Garden in 1970. And I stopped at
                  a secondhand bookshop (€2 for 1, €3 for 2, €5 for 3) which conveniently supplied
                  me with a 1903 volume of Lecciones de Lengua Castellana, and a book in Catalan
                  about the Catalan Templars. You can guess how much those cost me. </p>
               <p>Tomorrow it's six hours on the train to Malaga, where I gather they're expecting
                  me along with Daniel Gile, who is (in)famous in interpreting circles but I have
                  never met, only heard about.</p>
               <p>So be it. </p>
               <p>A demain</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4">
               <head>2015-01-28</head>
               <quote>CHAPTER XLVII. OF THE STRANGE MANNER IN WHICH DON QUIXOTE OF LA MANCHA WAS CARRIED
                  AWAY ENCHANTED, TOGETHER WITH OTHER REMARKABLE INCIDENTS</quote>
               <p>Just realised that in yesterday's account, there was no Cervantes (in spirit much,
                  but literally none). So this morning let us pose remedy, when finally ensconced in
                  my seat in the AVE for the six hours from Barcelona to Malaga. Not as easy as it
                  sounds: a luggage scanner, then two ladies at the information desk who assure me
                  that yes, in Preferente I will be fed en route, then a queue with ticket check
                  before being allowed onto the escalator down to the platform, then a walk along
                  the platform past about 25 Talgo coaches before reaching number 1. Moral: never
                  allow less than 15 minutes to get an AVE. Breakfast on the way to the station was
                  excellent - coffee con leche and croissant for a mere 2 euros with all the market
                  workers, incessantly prattling barman, and a quick walk round the (covered) market
                  revealed lots of fish, and various stands specialising in cooked vegetables,
                  mainly pulses. But I am going to be dined (and wined) by RENFE.</p>
               <p>A near-empty train, at any rate here in Preferente: one Spanish gent, now another
                  latecomer taking the seat next to mine, and an elderly English couple clutching a
                  copy of Great Railway Journeys of the World. I move nearer to them for prospects
                  of polite conversation. So far a newspaper, a hot towel - and a menu which appears
                  to describe lunch rather than breakfast, given the range of complimentary
                  alcoholic beverages listed. Breakfast is served on leaving Tarragona at 9, simply
                  consisting of fruit juice, yoghurt, potato omelette, bacon, mushrooms, rolls
                  (white and brown), croissants and limitless coffee, with a chocolate for afters.
                  Feeling decidedly full as we roll across the plain to Saragozza at a rather bumpy
                  299km/h (I didn't know Talgos could go so fast). Spain is still covered with
                  windmills, now generating electricity rather than grinding corn. Unfortunately
                  Talgos don't tilt, unlike the now alas defunct Italian Pendolino, otherwise the
                  Quixotian analogy would be perfect.</p>
               <p>Olive upon olive grove flies by at 12.40 and coming up to Cordoba, having skirted
                  Madrid from afar. Now facing a quarter bottle of Rueda Verdejo as (let us presume)
                  aperitif. Nice. As is the real glass, just as was the real cutlery at breakfast.
                  Spoon stolen. Finally found a touch screen with a map in the next coach, to the
                  gratitude of the great train journeyer and his lady, who only have one that dates
                  back to the pre-AVE epoch. They're going to Granada to spend a week in the hills,
                  having left Ebbsfleet yesterday morning and reached Barcelona in time for dinner
                  last night. Impressive. But I have just found a candidate title for the last
                  instalment of the current trip, of which herewith a preview, should you care:</p>
                 <quote> CHAPTER XXXV. WHICH TREATS OF THE HEROIC AND PRODIGIOUS BATTLE DON QUIXOTE HAD
                  WITH CERTAIN SKINS OF RED WINE, AND BRINGS THE NOVEL OF "THE ILL-ADVISED
                  CURIOSITY" TO A CLOSE.</quote>
               <p>PS. Having arrived in Malaga, I can say that it was not the aperitif. Or at any
                  rate, no lunch followed. Had to make do with the yoghurt not eaten at breakfast.
                  Such is life it seems, even in Preferente. But of Malaga, more tomorrow. Bearing
                  on Charles's telephone call, the street singers, the keys to the inn, Goliath
                  cement, the ne'er completed metro, and the all-very-close-by Costa de Sol
                  (so-called) with its retired English middle classes. Home from home, I hear you
                  say! For Pam: the catalan farton still comes at €2 for 10 in Barcelona, but none
                  yet heard (of) here in malaga.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5">
               <head>2015-01-30</head>
               <p>Today's will be brief in the extreme. In Malaga I have discovered the brand new
                  Metro, as the fastest way to get to the University, which was meant to run into
                  the city centre and ran into roman ruins instead, hence is currently used by
                  hardly anybody as it stops a mile and a half away (20 minutes brisk walk from the
                  Malaga Marriott hotel, of which, beyond Don Quixote's "You are a stupid, scurvy
                  innkeeper", many other if perhaps less telling insults would be justified). Used
                  the metro this evening to escape from the tapas party on campus and come back to
                  finish working on my paper for tomorrow. After all the bits of fried fish, the
                  rest of dinner thus takes the form of the instance of Las Legitimas y Acreditadas
                  Tortas de Aceite de Ines Rosales (Marca Registrada), Calle Real 102, Castilleja de
                  la Cuesta, Telefono 30, which I secreted from breakfast - not that I have any idea
                  where CdelaC might be, pretty small one would say from the phone number. Ines, you
                  should be warned, is a registered trademark - presumably not to be confused with
                  any of the other Rosales which may be knocking around the locality. Visita nuestra
                  tienda "on line" <ref
                     target="http://www.inesrosales.com/">www.inesrosales.com</ref> for more. Oh yes, 
                  and I promised Charles' phone call
                  last night, in which he rather shyly announced that he was getting married on
                  April 11 in Pescara town hall, and asked me to come. On learning of this, his
                  third matrimonial adventure, a losing battle to avoid replying Again? So have duly
                  booked my train ticket for the occasion, lost in admiration for his undiminishable
                  optimism. But for all the rest you will just have to wait until tomorrow post
                  presentation. Sorry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6">
               <head>2015-01-31</head>
               <p>Like many conferences of my experience, the reception desk at this one is
                  populated by winsome female undergraduates in slave labour, four of whom accosted
                  me upon arrival, requesting my immediate participation in a series of selfies, in
                  which, "flinging modesty aside" (Don Quixote, chap. XVI), I duly acquiesced, and
                  which you may or may not see in due course according to developments. Very
                  flattering. Only later did I discover that tomorrow, a prize will be awarded for
                  the best selfie of the conference. At the cocktail party last night I was taken
                  aside and informed that they expect to win the prize - on what basis I know not.
                  Further flattery this morning following my presentation, when I was taken aside
                  with the words "your talk was awful" (a mishearing - what she said she had said
                  was "your talk was awesome"). Ah well, I was only lecturing on speech
                  collocations. But it seemed generally well received, and now I can get down to the
                  social programme and the serious business of getting myself invited to other nice
                  places in Spain as soon as possible. Meantime good cold tomato soup called porra
                  for lunch. On-campus curiosities include: (1) framed documents pinned up in the
                  bar with names and pictures of all the graduates in that subject that year, one of
                  which includes the improbably named Ms Holly Ramirez Snowball, (2) a windswept
                  botanical garden with vast quantities of 2-foot high Privet Hedges, (3) adverts
                  for the Criminology Institute's course in Private Detection (Holmes from Holmes).
                  And more anon. With Mrs Nida, and the rapidly accumulating (numerically) curses on
                  the hostelry whereat I am unfortunately lodged.</p>
               <p>And how right you are, Pam&amp;Philip: thanks for the reassurance!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7">
               <head>2015-01-31</head>
               <p>The Marriott hotel of Malaga, as well as room keys that unlock on about 20% of
                  attempts, bath plugs which don't unplug, and wifi access which has to be renewed
                  every 24 hours at reception, also boasts two types of highly disappointing sausage
                  for breakfast. Oh yes, and they've also just told me that my keys no longer work
                  because I was leaving today, which of course I wasn't, haven't, won't and shan't.
                  After first demanding my credit card, they now say they confused me with someone
                  else. This morning was the last morning of the conference, and I snoozed through
                  the last plenary (in Spanish) and smiled at Mrs Eugene Nida who had chatted me up
                  all the previous evening at the gala dinner from which I escaped before the
                  dancing got serious, and has today given me a signed copy of her biography of her
                  husband (a famous figure in translation history). Most people seem to have gone
                  away already, except for the orange-jacketed security staff on the Metro, who
                  travel in pairs on nearly all the 2-coach trains and hang about in nearly all the
                  stations. Unclear whether this testifies to an excess of criminality in Malaga or
                  a total absence of same, or is simply a crash measure to reduce unemployment.</p>
               <p>But the big news of the day is: we won the best selfie prize! Me and the four
                  girls working at the desk, one of whom actually took it. You'll have to just
                  believe this extraordinary achievement for the moment, as I don't have an
                  electronic version to hand/eye, just a framed print and a piece of paper
                  certifying our glorious victory. But if you can get onto Twitter "citando la
                  cuenta del congreso (@AIETI7) y usando el hashtag <ref>#selfieAIETI7</ref>", 
                  who knows, you may still find it. The young ladies got
                  all their friends to vote for it. Being Saturday, all the cafes on campus were
                  shut, so we couldn't even celebrate properly or otherwise. It started raining, and
                  I left weighed down with various certificates and strange objects - including a
                  silver(y) flower (apparently the symbol of Malaga) on a little plinth as a reward
                  for my keynote. More excess baggage.</p>
               <p>It is raining as the conference comes to a close and I pull out my K-way to cross
                  over to the underground station, which is very much above ground. Why return to
                  the hotel and get wet? Or indeed, why get wet and return to the hotel? So I
                  descend at the main station and go and look for the suburban platforms. These
                  offer (inter alia) an every-20-minute service to Fuengirola, calling at Victoria
                  Park and Torremolinos inter alia - rather similar to the line from Lisbon to
                  Cascais, only the architecture you catch sight of en route is even worse.</p>
               <p>So I went to admire the Costa de Sol, slightly intrigued by its anglicisation, had
                  lunch of escalope, fried egg tomatoes and chips, viewed the programme of the Salon
                  Varietes Theatre (the only English theatre in Southern Spain, they claim), admired
                  the advertising for the Spanish School (who teach Spanish as a foreign language,
                  and are clearly in much greater demand than schools of English). Walked along a
                  bit of the beach, marvelled at the swimmers, and then got the train back to Malaga
                  Centre station - a mere 10 minutes walk from the hotel, give or take a minute or
                  two.</p>
               <p>Talking/taking of which, I have not yet mentioned the Malaga traffic lights.</p>
               <p>There are many traffic lights in Malaga, given the unaccomplished metro (v.sopra,
                  passim). The majority of these not only show red and green (and yellow) aspects,
                  but also inform the benighted pedestrian as to his or her future prospects. This
                  advice takes the form of a two-digit number and a human figure, both displayed in
                  the same colour as the aspect. The first shows the number of seconds to elapse
                  before the light changes, the second any consequent need to move and at what
                  speed. Thus you may see the green number 73, which implies that you have 73
                  seconds to cross the road before the light changes and you may be squashed by an
                  automobile. Thus "You risk meeting your maker in 70 seconds" (by now), and the
                  green figure ambles slowly. But wait until 7 seconds - the green figure breaks
                  into a sprint which you are (I presume) advised to imitate. There is also the
                  optimistic side, however. If the light is red (for pedestrians), the red number
                  tells you how long you should wait before you can cross the road and avenge
                  yourself upon the vehicular traffic. What they haven't yet got sorted out is an
                  appropriate appearance of the figure preparing to cross: maybe stretching its
                  legs, touching its toes, circling, or simply covering a large yawn?</p>
               <p>Now evening. Quitapenas dry (Malaga seco) is not the greatest digestivo around.
                  That's what comes of being lured to things by their names, which I had interpreted
                  as an invitation to leave my sufferings behind, and which thus seemed generally
                  fitting. I will ask a Spaniard about this tomorrow. (Excuse me Mr Worthy Spaniard
                  in coach 32 place 5C, is your surname by any chance Panza? And your first
                  name?)</p>
               <p>Tomorrow morning I go to Cordoba, where I have been advised by a familiar (with
                  Cordoba, that is - she goes otherwise by name of Martha) that I should get a taxi
                  from the station to the mosque in order to get into the latter before 11 oclock
                  mass starts, and that if I'm late, then Santos, in front of the mosque, makes "the
                  best tortilla of all Spain" (cit). Watch this space.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8">
               <head>2015-02-01</head>
               <p>THE BEGINNING OF THE RETURN</p>
               <p>And, as Sancho reminds us the saying is, the dead to the grave and the living to
                  the loaf. The loaf in this case being Santos' tortilla, which is indeed excellent,
                  washed down with a San Miguel at 11.30, which is when we tourists are thrown out
                  of Cordoba cathedral to make way for the devout and sit on the steps outside the
                  bar. The devout emerge at 1.45, which seems the appropriate time to go home and
                  make lunch round here, and for me to head back to the station for my train to
                  Madrid. But the meszquita/cathedral is astonishing (well worth 6 euros for a taxi
                  and another 8 for entry). The contrast between the numberless moorish
                  pillars/arches stretching into the distance over brick floors and the vulgarity of
                  all the 16th century opulence of catholic spanish art and architecture carved into
                  the centre of it is unforgettable.</p>
               <p>Olga met me at Puerto Atacha - yet another Spanish railway station disguised as an
                  airport, with a good 400 yards of escalators, travelators and lengthy corridors
                  between carriage door and exit. For those who may not know her, Olga was brought
                  up bilingual (German and Spanish), added English and Italian, and had ended up
                  teaching German in Ancona University when I was there in 1989-91. She then married
                  Pablo, one of the Ancona teachers of Spanish, and the two of them moved to Madrid
                  about 20 years ago. She is a highly skilled accordion player. I've maintained
                  occasional contact with them, and I'm now in a hotel room just round the corner
                  from their small flat near the park, where I am assured that Pablo is preparing a
                  serious fish dinner. Meantime a stroll round the block has revealed: an antique
                  toy shop full of pre-war clockwork trains; two open greengrocers (it's Sunday
                  afternoon, but they seem to be a Chinese monopoly); and a coffee bar menu offering
                  Sandwhich (in various flavours, of course).</p>
               <p>It was still dark in Malaga at 8.15 when I got to the railway station after
                  getting lost, with a soap disguised as a golfball in my pocket as a final courtesy
                  from Messrs Marriott. The North Edge has just got too heavy, however, so the frame
                  of the selfie will perish in Madrid, and the fate of Mrs Nida's hagiography is
                  uncertain. Turista class is decidedly worse than Preferente, though I now know
                  quite a lot about Paco de Lucia's musical career on the TV. They have this nice
                  habit of giving tourists free earphones. Tomorrow is a Brueghel day, the other
                  side of the park. It's culture time! Not to mention dinner time!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9">
               <head>2015-02-02</head>
               <p>Just reached the point in Don Quixote (400th anniversary this year, the posters
                  from La Mancha proclaim) where Sancho ties Rocinante's legs together in order to
                  stop his master galloping off in the dark in search of a new adventure. For the
                  record, therefore, let me swear that today I have not seen or been on a single
                  train, tube or tram, or set foot in a station of any of these typologies - "See
                  there, senor! Heaven, moved by my tears and prayers, has so ordered it that
                  Rocinante cannot stir; and if you will be obstinate, and spur and strike him, you
                  will only provoke fortune, and kick, as they say, against the pricks." So instead,
                  following a giant croissant (served with knife and fork, given its dimensions) and
                  a surprisingly good café con leche for breakfast in a bar round the corner which
                  vaunted a shelf of 13 different gins (including no Gordons), I felt duly ready to
                  face the world and set off across the Buen Retiro, which resembles a Hyde Park
                  neatly running from St Pancras to Trafalgar Square, passing by the British Museum
                  half way, i.e. my chosen destination of the Prado. And no, I didn't tempt fortune
                  by going as far as Puerta Atocha, the StPancras of the analogy. I just got lost in
                  the park, while escaping a TV troupe near the Crystal Palace (sic), among the
                  unleashed joggers, cyclists, hounds, and various combinations of these categories.
                  Of which the most striking example was a very small dog drawing behind it a
                  miniature two-wheeled cart at no inconsiderable speed, which at first glance I
                  took for a tricycle, and only upon closer examination (of the doggie that is)
                  discovered its unfortunate three-leggedness. Only later too did I associate this
                  image with Brueghel's Wine of St Martin's day, where Martin is slicing his cloak
                  into two in order to give same to two legless cripples. So fortunately reached the
                  Prado with jacket intact. Only regretted having left woolly hat in hotel;
                  temperature siberian until the sun finally rose and the old ladies appeared in
                  little groups to feed the ducks. </p>
               <p>Two men getting into an Otis van told me how to get to the Prado but didn't give
                  me a lift (sorry). I joined the queue of those with reservations (the couple in
                  front had a similar piece of paper to me), a queue labelled "only lectures",
                  possibly because placed directly beneath a statue of Goya at whose feet lies a
                  voluptuous nude? After which we get to get tickets, and I become the first in the
                  next queue to get in to the real thing at 10. Thinks: this can't all be fun in the
                  rain.</p>
               <p>And so I get three hours to look at Breughel: The Triumph of Death and St Martin's
                  Wine, with occasional interruptions from the guided tours of Japanese tourists and
                  Spanish six-year-olds with yellow paint on their noses. In some ways these are
                  similar pictures, what with figures passing away in the one case and out in the
                  other. As often with B, there is a bird (a magpie?) perched at a key point from
                  which to view the scene, in the Triumph from upon a wheel at upper right where
                  someone is being broken, in St Martin's on the tree at upper mid-left above the
                  gully with a buttoned drunk flat on his back. But more of these tomorrow.</p>
               <p>After joining me for a small and rather liquid lunch in the museum across the road
                  (Pablo has gone off to Cuenta), Olga tries to take me to a gallery she likes, but
                  it turns out to be closed on <ref
                     target="https://www.facebook.com/HappyMondaysOnline/">
                     >Happy Mondays</ref>, it starts raining, and we have to make do with chatting
                  in assorted languages to our Bulgarian taxidriver. So we arrange to meet for
                  dinner, and here I am back in hotel. Have written a pile of postcards, taken them
                  to the Post Office, where they stamped them without stamps, and then stopped off
                  on the way back in the House of Cod. The latter provided me with a small tin of
                  Foie de Bacalao to take back to Italy. Then again at the Spy's Shop, outside which
                  stands a Bogart figure brandishing a revolver, and who sell phonetapping and
                  recording equipment (should have enquired if they did automatic transcription).
                  Picked up a catalogue to read in the train (sorry, the T-word just escaped me)
                  tomorrow. A tapassy dinner with Olga in two local bars, drinking Galician wine and
                  eating assorted bits of ham, fish, tomato etcetera. And now apparently it's going
                  to snow tomorrow over most of northern Spain. Sic transit mundus. (Will see
                  whether transeunt trenos.)</p>
               <p>Good night.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10">
               <head>2015-02-03</head>
                <p>And that's it. Farewell Hotel Alcala (whose slogan "wake up to a better world"
                  seems somewhat optimistic), musing on why, as I get older, does it take me ever
                  longer to get washed and dressed of a morning? A return to yesterday's bar for
                  breakfast and today a tortilla with 3 slices of bread (still 15 gins) and we begin
                  our 36 hours of travel back across Europe. Will we be followed by Malaga-trained
                  private detectives with (un)sophisticated eavesdropping equipment purchased at the
                  Tienda del Espia? But first Madrid must conclude with Brueghel again. The Prado
                  opens at 10, and Wine and Death await. Will try to write something about both on
                  the train. The skeleton playing the viol, the one playing the hurdy-gurdy, the one
                  wearing clothes taken from their victim. What is in no doubt is the physical
                  strength of these figures of bones, not least of the two mounted figures, with
                  their scythes poised to strike.</p>
               <p>But I have said nothing of the Buen Retiro, where I again managed to get lost and
                  come out on the side I had gone in. Saw Alfonso the peacemaker, and Yrigoyen,
                  creator of the Dia de la Raza en America, a triumph of Spanish colonialism. And
                  Jascinto Verdaguez, the greatest Spanish epic poet if you believe the statue. A
                  blue sky at sunrise, as I find myself humming Buddy Holly's Raining in my heart.
                  And indeed before reaching the Prado, and avoiding the signs to Baby Jesus Square
                  (sic), it has started raining again. But I now know the queuing routine and am
                  thus able to avoid the worst, pausing to examine the Goya statue in greater
                  detail, with inscription "the sleep of reason generates monsters". Not quite sure
                  whether this is meant to refer to the opulent nude over whom he towers as well as
                  the shadowy figures on the other sides of the plinth.</p>
               <p>Started with St Martin's wine, which is a pyramid of entwined figures around a
                  vermilion barrel. Martin himself with horse, cloak and cripples forms another,
                  lower pyramid to its right. Taken together, an isoceles triangle, whose apex is an
                  upraised emptied jar. The immediate foreground at the foot of the triangle is
                  almost empty, highlighting the lost shoe of one of the horizontal drunks. And
                  above the other horizontal drunk in the distance, a tree with Breughel's
                  inevitable bird perching, setting one diagonal to the barrel and Martin's horse's
                  white bottom, and another down through the isolated figures on the lower left.
                  It's as if there were three different worlds - one of the charity, one of the
                  party, one of the various single figures and pairs reacting in different ways. The
                  overall geometrical form of the throng recalls that of the towers of Babel.</p>
               <p>The triumph of death is more frightening the more you look. All the musical
                  references - the hurdygurdy, the bells, the drums, the trumpets being played by
                  skeletons variously scattered over the picture, leave little space to the living
                  lute-player and singer at bottom right - ironically accompanied by the skeleton
                  with viol. The bird which sits on the white horse's back - doing what? In Das
                  Elster auf den Galgen, the magpie is a point of view, the artist's eye, and here
                  too perhaps. There are various Boschian animals around the burning tower in the
                  centre - what the two ?human figures on top of the tower are doing, or their caged
                  and escaping birds, I don't know. The comic section - skeletons wearing clothes
                  seemingly stolen from their victims, offering skulls for supper, as the jester
                  hides under the table - only emphasises the countless violent deaths all over the
                  place. Vast cavalry and infantry armies hopelessly outnumber the living, including
                  those being thrust into what seems a giant gas chamber; in the top left hand area
                  skeletons cut down the trees. There isn't a green leaf to be seen. Under the
                  arches on the left, a skeleton sits looking rather bored, head in hands and
                  looking out of the picture. Clearly seen it all before. Going back to the bird, I
                  can only interpret it all as a claim that art is, in its limited way, a potential
                  opponent of mortality. On which note, I head for the botanical garden en route for
                  Puerte de Atocha and the VIP club bar, to which my ticket apparently entitles me
                  access.</p>
               <p>We leave on time at 13.30 in an AVE - another symbolic bird, built into the logo.
                  Seven hours to go to Nimes, and fortunately not full, so I abandon my reserved
                  seat which is (a) back to engine; (b) with no window; (c) with a table which only
                  goes horizontal if I move my feet into the corridor. I wait to see whether anyone
                  gets on and claims that nice seat I am now in at Guadalajara, Saragozza,
                  Tarragona, Barcellona, Figueres, Perpignan, Narbonne or Montpelier. All very black
                  leather and luxurious. Are they going to provide lunch? We come to a halt before
                  the platform end for no apparent reason, then restart. AVEs don't have wifi. I
                  badly lack a railway map of Madrid, having really no idea how we leave heading
                  south and end up heading north. I think round the east side, insasmuch as we
                  generally seem to be turning left.</p>
               <p>Guadalajara is in the middle of nowhere after 25 minutes, and there is still no
                  sign of lunch. Instead we have an old black and white movie of bullfights and
                  flamenco, without soundtrack, but occasional subtitling in both Spanish and
                  French. On the music channel, we have Wagner. That's what I call an international
                  train for you. Meantime we progress towards Saragozza, and the world becomes white
                  with snow. Ah well, lunch will just have to be what I stole from the VIP lounge at
                  Puerta de Atocha. On a wander along to the cafeteria in coche 4, which involves
                  passing through Coche 2, I receive unconsoling information: had I had a seat in
                  coche 2 rather than coche 1, I would have been given lunch, since coche 1 is
                  occupied by holders of French 1st class tickets, coche 2 by those of Spanish
                  Preferente tickets. Next time, sit in coche 2. Now there's discrimination for you.
                  All we want now is to find out what king, Christian or pagan, is at war and has a
                  beautiful daughter.</p>
               <p>Some chapters of Cervantes later, the sun is sinking above a bank of cloud, pink
                  light over the snow on the Pyrenees. Figueres, a piece of double-gauge railway -
                  three rails, one shared, two distinct for Spanish gauge and standard gauge. We're
                  near the end of Spain, an almost totally empty train, and still another three
                  hours to Nimes. A beautiful sunset, fleecy little low clouds, heavier dark banks
                  in the distance, and we're in the tunnel. Near dark on the other side as we brake
                  for Perpignan. End of high speed for today. An uneventful trip so far.</p>
               <p>But in Nice it is snowing. And what did I have for dinner? You name it, Cod</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11">
               <head>2015-02-04</head>
               <p>And last. Bid farewell to the rather sad-looking English couple who run the Hotel
                  des Tuilleries in Nimes, a quick walk round (not around) the Roman Arena - I had
                  forgotten how well conserved it is, and indeed the difference between round and
                  around - and then up the magnificent station approach from the Place Charles de
                  Gaulle, the statue in which is not of de Gaulle. One of the most splendid station
                  approaches in the world, about 50 yards wide, the middle 30 yards of which for
                  pedestrians, the sides for buses, all of which seem to be going to the unlikely
                  sounding (or better looking) Pisse Vin. Outside the station, the Cafe Fleurs du
                  Mal provides a very hasty breakfast, as I realise my train leaves in exactly 6
                  minutes. It goes to Dijon, past about a mile of the Nimes cemetery (Brueghel
                  docet), then crawling round the triangle leaving Nimes for Tarascon where they are
                  inserting the new avoiding line to Montpelier, and then up past Avignon, gazing
                  out on the snow capped hills of Provence. An odd sight. It is very cold. I see the
                  weather forecast today is for 30cm of snow (a)round Vergato, so I shan't get home
                  tonight. Either Bologna, or else straight to Forli where I have appointments
                  tomorrow morning, and when further snow is forecast.</p>
               <p>It's odd to be going back. What to? Ah well, I should write up my Malaga
                  presentation on corpora and interpreting for the lovely Gloria Corpas (sic) to
                  publish, and I must seriously do some heavy labour sorting out Daniela's study,
                  deciding what to take to Vergato, what to Pavullo, what to throw away. Camilla was
                  making great progress on her clothes and miscellaneous objects when I left,
                  Fabrizio has promised many more cardboard boxes. A useful if highly sobering
                  occupation until access to Liserna becomes possible once more. Oh yes, and I must
                  apply for a new passport, otherwise will soon be imprisoned in Italy.</p>
               <p>Ah yes, for the record. Restaurant Nicholas in Rue Poise at Nimes, run by a
                  formidable lady of about eighty, a tasty terrine maison, the cod was excellent,
                  washed down by Cotes du Gard, and concluded with a sliver of Roquefort.
                  Recommended.</p>
               <p>That I think was Valence TGV, snow-covered and non-stopped. In twenty minutes we
                  shall be in Lyon Part Dieu, where I have nothing whatever to do for two hours.
                  Maybe I can get an earlier train to Chambery, he thinks, and yes, the Accueil tell
                  me it's allowed. The high spot of PartDieu is the pianist. French railways have
                  now equipped all their main stations with Yamaha pianos for anyone to play as and
                  how they want, and this player is quite good. But having helped an old lady up the
                  escalator, it's off to first stop Aix les bains. Past Culoz (one of my favouritely
                  named railway junctions), where I used to get off and spend the night in the
                  decrepit station hotel when there were still through trains from Turin to Calais.
                  A long time ago.</p>
               <p>Today is just a second class day. Throughout, but with only a couple of hours in
                  each train. This regionale is completely empty, so who cares. One lady with
                  bicycle and a bad cough, and that's all else in the coach. Heading out along the
                  Rhone. But why go to Chambery again when you can explore Aix les bains
                  instead?</p>
               <p>After Amberieu (junction with the old line coming from Paris, Bourg, Macon to
                  proceed to Geneva, Chambery, and Modane, we are surrounded by the ever steeper
                  foothills of the Alps, and several inches of snow as we wind up the wooded valley.
                  The Bar Sport, a row of houses along the road, their backs against the
                  mountainside, and here's Culoz, where we turn South and leave the line to Geneva.
                  A nice station, with ever wider platforms on two sides of the triangle.</p>
               <p>Aix isn't bad, at any rate out of season. The hotel Annapolis might even be a nice
                  place to stay. I find the market, with a very long cheese stall boasting even
                  Taleggio and Shropshire Blue, and in the middle Vacherin and Tomme de Savoie to
                  take back with me. Waiting for the Plat du Jour to arrive in the brasserie
                  opposite the station, hopefully in time for the next train to Chambery. Avoiding
                  the temptation to stop off in the Zanzi Bar. The television is full of the
                  terrorist attack in Nice. And again, the reaction is proposals to control the
                  Internet.</p>
               <p>Suggestions for censorship on my verbosity please. Have successfully transferred
                  to the TGV in Chambery, coming up to Modane in various feet of snow, some twenty
                  minutes late. Will I make my Turin connection? Will anyone come and talk to me now
                  I have found a large empty table next to the buffet? And what will Italy hold? The
                  Mont Cenis pass is FermÃ©, a notice announces. These and other questions may or
                  may not be answered in our continuation from Monteverdi, il ritorno di Ulisse in
                  patria. Meantime Modane, smoothly, a crawl through the Mont Cenis tunnel, and a
                  similar amount of snow. Bardonecchia, and a noisy discussion between what I take
                  to be the French barlady and the Italian barman, who seem to be swapping over at
                  the frontier, and listing out loud the number of each kind of sandwich which is
                  crossing the border/changing hands. A small and expensive bottle of Soave for
                  company, a brief discussion with the staff on the chances of catching up time on
                  the descent, a misty day. No sign of Italian border checks. Or indeed of any
                  ticket collection.</p>
               <p>But I make my connection, and again manage to move myself to a place with a big
                  table. I can perhaps conclude appropriately(?) by narrating a splendid house in
                  the Avenue de Verdun, near the station in Aix. Completely painted on a wall with
                  three storeys, ground floor a Herboristerie with lots of pots and a shed with a
                  man with a plank on his shoulder coming out, on the first floor a window with
                  flowers and another with a gent in officer's uniform looking out, on the second a
                  lady leaning out to water flowers, and another window with a cat. I thought it was
                  all real for at least 10 seconds. A good point to conclude: farewell</p>
            </div>

         </div>
         <div xml:id="Liserna-LaVergne">
            <head>Destination LaVergne (April 2015)</head>
            <div>
               <head>2015-04-18</head>

               <p>Greetings to our uncounted readers. Off again, again in company of Cervantes.
                  Packed yesterday, and woke up early so just had time to do a dry run through of my
                  talk via skype for the tinvim conference in Tunis, scheduled for 1230-1330 today.
                  Seems more or less ok, have to do anyway, so it's turn off the gas and stroll down
                  the hill with rucksack and rubbish, the latter consigned to the (nearest) bin at
                  the next group of houses after the church, stifled sobs over the remains of the
                  six 200-year old oaks which the philistines have just cut down. A sentiment shared
                  by the vet, who picks me up a few yards further on, so we discuss his manuscript
                  recounting his farmyard childhood, which he gave me to read in the hope of advice
                  on its potential publication. I practice my fibbing skills and suggest changes to
                  the footnotes. So I am early for the train, time for a capuccino, say hello to
                  Marco returning from the shops, leave a scrawled message for his wife Sandra and
                  cousins from Rome. The train is uneventful, as usual, as is the bus to Daniela's
                  now nearly empty flat, where </p>
               <p>the first thing I find on Skype is a message saying they want to postpone me to
                  one o'clock. So I remind them that I have to leave at 1.30. And so they connect me
                  and I start talking at 12. About 10 minutes into my spiel they tell me they
                  haven't been able to hear me for the last 5, and haven't seen my slides for the
                  last 3. Sit and wait. At 12.30 they tell me they have moved on to the next item on
                  the programme, due to "internet problems". Ah well, three days preparation wasted,
                  who cares? Other adventures of equal or greater preparation immediately await.
                  Just time for a sandwich at the bar before my taxi arrives and takes a devious
                  route to the station. Never mind, my Italo Smart Extra Large is on time, and at
                  3.30 I am in the SNCF booking office in Milano Porta Garibaldi station to demand a
                  Carte Senior, which they can't put my photo on as they are out of sncf regulation
                  sticky tape. I should ask them to do that in France (and I'm glad to say the
                  booking clerk in Modane bemusedly obliged before closing up for the weekend). So I
                  then ask the lady for 9 discounted tickets for my journeys from Modane to Gueret,
                  and then back from Gueret to Modane, and in about 20 minutes she exchanges them in
                  instalments with various large bundles of cash. I complement her on her efficiency
                  in finding places she'd never heard of and say should I send her a postcard (the
                  answer is yes - her name is Exxxa and she lives at xxxxx near Lambrate). </p>
               <p>So now it's holiday time, window gazing as we staidly progress on the traditional
                  line from Milan to Turin, largely flanked by rectangular paddy fields, tilled from
                  Novara to Vercelli, then flooded from Vercelli to Santhia, then tilled again from
                  Santhia to Chivasso. Who eats it all? Ah, but you forget the popularity of risotto
                  milanese in these parts. Why aren't we on the high speed line? Because the French
                  refuse to install Italy's expensive radio signalling system on their TGVs. </p>
               <p>Ah, Vercelli. It all comes back now. O tempora o mores (more time then). I first
                  went to Vercelli aged 19 to look at the Vercelli book, one of the four extant
                  manuscripts of anglo-saxon poetry. Twas my first trip to Italy on my own, I think
                  on the proceeds of the Kingston Oliphant prize for Language, nearly 50 years ago
                  (49 to be precise). Nostalgia sets in further later on as under a hazy sun
                  climbing out of Turin there peers the mountaintop with the Sacra di San Michele,
                  up to which I climbed on the same trip (had I confused it with Mont St Michel in
                  Normandy), and where I was taken in by the family who lived there after I
                  discovered there were no longer any monks to provide me with a cell. Other
                  window-gazing highlights include two rusting steam engines stored on a branch line
                  beneath a motorway bridge; a circular tower with a large engraved sign "Casa del
                  vecchio P. Perozzi" (translation old folk's home or old folks' home?); the
                  unlikely station Livorno Ferraris (from which you would need a Ferrari to reach
                  Livorno in less than half a day, sorry, that was far too easy). All is relatively
                  tranquil, until ... you should know that on the other side of the gangway of coach
                  2 (first class) from me are seated two middle-aged japanese(?) gentlemen. When we
                  stop in Turin (timetabled 2 minutes), I don't really notice the last two
                  passengers getting on, nor their rapidly alighting again, now clutching a bag
                  snatched from the rack above the heads of the two Japanese. The Japanese don't
                  notice either, but ... it seems the police, amazingly, do. The Japanese are hauled
                  from the train, and much window-gazing takes place for the next 20 minutes until
                  the Japanese reappear with their bag to be greeted by applause from the rest of
                  the coach. Twice in a week in Italy, never in their 20 times in France, the
                  victims comment to their predominantly French audience. We leave Turin 24 minutes
                  late, "due to a police intervention" in 3 languages. The Japanese even shake my
                  hand when I leave at Modane, by that stage only 4 minutes late, after the last bit
                  of the climb to the Frejus under bright sunlight on snowstreaked alps. Moral:
                  watch your luggage when travelling first class on Milan-Paris TGVs during the
                  Turin stop.</p>
               <p>Modane is dull. Apart from the museum of mechanical pianos, which is however
                  closed until May 11. The Hotel Le Commerce is deservedly deserted. Slowly relaxing
                  into French again, realising that I do understand quite a lot at any rate in
                  restaurants and booking offices. For yes, the Modane booking office was still open
                  at 7.20, and kindly stuck my photo onto my carte senior with regulation tape (if a
                  thing's worth saying once, ...). A plat of ham cheese and salad at the La Caprice
                  restaurant (like everything else in Modane, just opposite the station), even if
                  the local in the Hotel Le Commerce (also just opposite the station) swore it was
                  closed. But my room looks not at the station but at the bare hillside on the other
                  side of the river, with a splendid late 19th century villa. I have not however
                  seen Modane's most famous monument, la maison penchée: <ref
                     target="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3D-rIjvgRlnu4%26fbclid%3DIwAR0wKASyZrmcWy4NT0Ig4gQarCsDtIsAvTXnZT7VtWhTNOzQCEC_4czANxk&amp;h=AT1U7VgloLjF-z0NlVqfORhNo_kmT1tKW2L1j8d4FhIdmOZej1A5PgMae57eGO2_cmVhcnnwD-9Oyh3KjTZ7PDZNtsllvgoU9GpeoYBQH8SAKEOqjjGl-ODIMz6vLn4U3bP6eb_W75hUn_LchIjyQe9DyxA5eCDJLeQT"
                     >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-rIjvgRlnu4</ref> . </p>
               <p>Sancho Panza tied Rocinante's hind legs together to force Quixote to wait for the
                  dawn, and likewise (or inversely) am I tied by a 7am train to catch from Voie C
                  (wherever that is). Good night all.</p>
               <p>PS. Happy Birthday, Fi !</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-04-19</head>
               <p>2. Sunday morning at a quarter to seven in Modane is dull, and the hotel bar is
                  still closed, notwithstanding the fact that I paid for a breakfast coffee last
                  night. Little do they know that I will return to Modane next Thursday afternoon
                  demanding same. Nothing seems open, so stick my room key in their postbox, cross
                  the road, stamp my ticket and head for Voie C in the wake of one other intending
                  passenger on the 0701 to Lyon (Part Dieu). Fortunately, this has a breakfast stop
                  of 20 minutes at Chambery, where a Petit Formule of coffee/juice/croissant in the
                  Bar de Savoie 2 outside the station significantly improves things, and I can
                  reboard the train along with many Chamberians(?) wondering just how turntables for
                  electric locomotives actually work, as the catenary must revolve too. And ponder
                  other questions of more immediate import, such as</p>
               <p>- Where is La Vergne? Why is it taking me three days to get there? Will I ever?
                  What may befall en route? And why are there no Brueghels on this trip? The sncf
                  may have answers to only some of these questions, as we emerge from the tunnel to
                  Aiguelette-Le-Lac. And in any case, what are the rules of hyphenation in French
                  (when in doubt, particularly with place names, hyphenate everything?) Sur
                  le-Pont-de-Beauvoisin (our next stop), what do they get up to?</p>
               <p>Had been planning to spend my time in Lyon buying tickets for rest of trip, but
                  Exxxa in Milan did all that for me, so will be able to explore the Parc de la tete
                  d'or, seemingly the only thing near Part Dieu one might want to see. Along with
                  further coffee. The parc turns out to have botanical gardens and unveiled threats
                  - Il est formellement interdit de nourrir les canards. The canards and their
                  multitudinous offspring look pretty well just the same. Walk back past the sadly
                  closed station of Brotteaux for the 12.10 three car collection of single diesel
                  cars which runs nonstop to St-Etienne and all stations thereafter. Uneventful,
                  though lunch is just the remaining bread and cheese in my bag, as it was too early
                  to follow up any of Lou's restaurant suggestions, which were all closed on Sundays
                  anyway. </p>
               <p>Le Puy en Velay. Strange volcanic pillars towering up, surmounted by statues and
                  monuments. Lots of very steep steps to get anywhere. Last here some 25 years ago
                  at New Year meeting up with my girlfriend of the time on my way back to Italy from
                  England. Cold wet and miserable as far as I recall, with a lousy dinner. Le Puy
                  was a place of pilgrimage, with a statue of a black madonna later found to be the
                  Egyptian Isis, and now one of the main starting points for Compostella. I go and
                  say hello to the statue of St James and admire the romanic sculpture in the
                  cathedral. Le Puy also boasts an open souvenir shop with postcards and a main
                  square branch of Credit Mutuel, whose ATM refuels me with cash from my Paris bank
                  account, still boasting a four-figure sum ten years after anything was paid into
                  it - one of the miracles of not being here that often, credit mutuel not having
                  many branches, and my havin forgotten either the card, the PIN, or both when
                  finding myself in front of one.</p>
               <p>Another twin diesel, this time in green for Auvergne, takes me to Arvant, just
                  south of Clermont Ferrand, through superb gorge scenery, variously ruined mountain
                  chateaux and squeaky curves twisting along the valleys. Arvant is another place
                  I've been before, this time on my own, around 30 years ago, to retrace Stevenson's
                  Travels with a Donkey on foot. Then I got the train from Clermont to Langeac,
                  which was where he started from. As I type, we're just running into the junction
                  with that line at St George d'Aurac (the station nameplates don't hyphenate this
                  time). Nobody gets on or off, just masses of whitethorn flowering both sides of
                  the single track. Very festive. After Arvant it starts raining, the railway turns
                  primitive with wooden sleepers, chairs and fishplates, so we clickety-click our
                  unwelded way down to Aurillac, again with some wonderful scenery. So I recommend
                  Le Puy-Arvant-Neussages as a way of crossing France, it just takes time. </p>
               <p>Aurillac I'm less sure. It's twenty minutes walk along the Rue de la Republique to
                  reach La Square, which is where all the three hotels are. Drizzling as I passed
                  the hospital and the various associated funeral directors, lots of grey frontage
                  and no one around. La Renaissance is one of those hotels where things tend not to
                  work, but in compensation provided quite a nice dinner of Tete de veau, Tripoux
                  and Truffade, all of which claimed to be local. An early night is called for
                  however; there's another 7 o'clock train in the morning which provides a Paris
                  connection for the locals. Sweet dreams.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-04-20</head>
               <p>3. Still drizzling at 6.30 as I set off up the hill for the station, thinking that
                  Le Renaissance could do with one, having failed to provide my wakeup call. The
                  funeral directors are all closed (a good sign?) but the newsagents are open, and
                  one also has a bar for a coffee. Another one-coach diesel awaits, this time with 8
                  passengers, as we set off down to Brive, on one of the most impressive bits of
                  train journey of my life. For about 35 kilometres, from Laroquebrau to Laval de
                  Cere, the train overhangs the river down the winding gorge de cere, mainly
                  supported by walls built up from the river bank. It only crosses the river once,
                  at an unused crossing loop at a closed station called La Martine, and apart from
                  the occasional empty railway hut, and one small hydroelectric plant, there is no
                  sign of human habitation for the entire distance, trees trees and more trees and
                  occasional waterfalls, plus a kilometre or so at 10km/h, presumably because of
                  falling rocks. Very impressive, even if on a grey misty morning. Yes, Le Puy en
                  Velay to Brive La Gaillarde is a spectacular way to cross France.</p>
               <p>When the valley finally spreads out into a plain we stop in a small town with
                  enormous plank-making factories, presumably from the not inconsiderable forests
                  just traversed. More passengers appear too, all heading for the Paris express at
                  Brive-la-Gaillarde, along with those coming in on six other trains from
                  surrounding localities within the same ten minutes. Five minutes after the last of
                  these, the 14-coach loco-hauled express from Toulouse pulls in, over a hundred
                  passengers clamber on, and after a two-minute stop off we head for Limoges through
                  the countryside at a steady ninety miles an hour. Very impressive organisation,
                  and a striking example of how Paris-centred things are: the next train at Brive
                  after these seven is over two hours later. When we stop in Limoges I go in search
                  of the restaurant car, but no, the lady ticket collector I encounter in the
                  Service section tells me there isn't one, just a compartment occupied by boxes and
                  a hot water machine which looks singularly incapable of producing anything
                  resembling coffee. Yes, I think, I have done the right thing in bringing two packs
                  of Kimbo Neapolitan blend as a gift for friends Lilette and Lou. </p>
               <p>I also ask the lady ticket collector if I have understood correctly the
                  announcement about La Souterraine, namely that you should be in the front half of
                  this lengthy train if you want to get off. She tells me it doesn't stop there and
                  I must change here at Limoges, a peculiar claim given that I have a reserved seat
                  to La Souterraine on the train we're on. Her colleague tells her I am right and
                  she apologises, clutching her paper cup of clearly ineffectual coffee. And half an
                  hour later, I am getting off the train from the Service coach, ready to hit the
                  Grand Hotel which is not, but where the tables outside are variously occupied with
                  patrons. It's 1030, no croissants left, a wander around past the cathedral, buy
                  stamps at the post office, postcards at the tobacconist's, and back down to the
                  bus for Felletin which awaits the arrival of the express from Paris, and off to St
                  Vaury, the nearest place to Bussieres, where there is a taxi office just opposite
                  the bus stop. A lady taxidriver whisks me to Bussieres church, opposite which is
                  the sole and excellent eating place in Bussieres, where Lou and Lilette await: we
                  are in time for lunch, which you can't get after 1pm. </p>
               <p>
                  <ref
                     target="https://encrypted-tbn3.gstatic.com/images?q=tbn%3AANd9GcRDRh8Tf6kVNLM8yycQFa0-reMuYEuopKDH4Tfmef_c9-VcPEMvKw&amp;fbclid=IwAR31NCBRHw87QfWZ5qKnGLJCnJRsYcFvlUSemQuXttIA4MzowaR4SrD3iK8"
                     >https://encrypted-tbn3.gstatic.com/images…</ref>
               </p>
               <p>A good lunch, some narrative, and then we walk to their house in La Vergne
                  (no-hyphen) along the rue de la gare <ref
                     target="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.gendep23.org%2FST-VAURY-c%2FBUSSIERE-DUNOISE%2Fimages%2Fagare_grd.jpg%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR3QjVfn2NAg7cx_EvCjEWfHbNpUuMj3Kk0E1oMbob50hNVrRDrVleT7SbY&amp;h=AT2lFR_lCUcckhFpxUOL7OMz3NpcNot3QLJMFfv4YAhODZCr6fo6L7w-bYGW_cV3EShYbvzA0xxo7MzEqw-6MFlziotZfVOOro183yqAEJ2_FMf5CHTVxKUoC9ruNcFaY1FMo0Px2r1cvSavInA2RNXZb3KVmqBUfpASvIvbUWT6fVc1Fg"
                     >http://www.gendep23.org/…/BUSSIERE-DUN…/images/agare_grd.jpg</ref> and then
                     <ref
                     target="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fencrypted-tbn2.gstatic.com%2Fimages%3Fq%3Dtbn%253AANd9GcQtXyC2gQKjLLPwbroQ97x3PpClY1K6tUMzAg7SV6Yr4m463oyE%26fbclid%3DIwAR0XA4_IhTWZJZCpUuLKm407-vkJo4DUNXxiXF4uHGd244-7RNHZT0Qj87Q&amp;h=AT0uCucxc5X5-3kPheLJ5jXJM6iwnyQwfAS3WEtHd-OZ2kFwfHbA9lVmNIeVw_V4hWDpGYbl3DfgFT3dXVlMd0f7R4-VBC61CaWSO04vA2Aj0wunsSAir9I4896HV5JWJhPwJpJTPX-tiSrXcH0LQvtXrlHwpFnUGiQm"
                     >https://encrypted-tbn2.gstatic.com/images…</ref> along the derelict railway
                  line to the foot of the Burnard garden <ref
                     target="http://perso.numericable.fr/j-mautrait/LaCreuseFerroviaire/LigneStSebastienGueret/PontRaillaVergne.jpg?fbclid=IwAR3NIlFg3AQ1yUk33VteN-mzmRazdGGYwHRnCA6IOnotsEPxeWIVdPqNj4M"
                     >http://perso.numericable.fr/…/LigneStS…/PontRaillaVergne.jpg</ref>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-04-22</head>
               <p>Day 4. In which we walk the line</p>
               <p>Lilette goes shopping with her friend Isabel in Dun-le-Palestel, Lou and I try to
                  cut the hedge and wait for the twice-a-week bread lady, known as La Superbe, who
                  appears with ordered pain complet. After which the two of us set out to continue
                  along the railway line in the direction of Monneger, which we never reach due to
                  an intervening field full of suspicious bulls and bullocks, and a diversion via
                  the village of Rissat, home to a well-tended Etang and an elderly English couple
                  intent on their gardening. At the point shown in the picture below we retrieve the
                  railway line for our return along a splendid broom-walled embankment, but then are
                  forced back onto a road again when it becomes a rubbish-filled cutting. <ref
                     target="http://perso.numericable.fr/j-mautrait/LaCreuseFerroviaire/LigneStSebastienGueret/PontRouteMonneger.jpg?fbclid=IwAR0sHqA54XvWuirpcthlR4kTQq--mEMWS8Nk_Fuezgtyp6gVGSqiipW-n8E"
                     >http://perso.numericable.fr/…/LigneSt…/PontRouteMonneger.jpg</ref>
               </p>
               <p>Finally we make our way across a field and two electric fences, and back along the
                  line to the bottom of the garden for lunch with Lilette.</p>
               <p>
                  <ref
                     target="http://p9.storage.canalblog.com/99/84/635675/94574273_o.jpg?fbclid=IwAR2ajLHZKK1Nm2UwpEhUI6WAlUgCJiVOEyHfmfThYr7EPZevcQ2SG976D9Y"
                     >http://p9.storage.canalblog.com/99/84/635675/94574273_o.jpg</ref>
               </p>
               <p>In the afternoon Lou practices on the dandelions with his newly purchased
                  strimmer, we restore the washing line to pristine glory, reduce another bit of
                  hedge, and then rabbit stew with Isabel who is driving back to blighty early in
                  the morning bearing sausages. A quiet day.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-04-23</head>
               <p>Days 5-6. Potatoes, memories, reservations</p>
               <p>One of the postcards on Mons. M__'s elderly but exhaustive site on the railways of
                  La Creuse shows Bussiere Dunoise station yard submerged in carts, apparently full
                  of potatoes to be sent by train to the front. Potatoes are big in this part of the
                  world. Not for nothing did Lilette, my first night in La Vergne, make an excellent
                  tortilla, reminding me of the last sampled opposite the cathedral in Cordova (the
                  best tortilla in all Spain, I was assured by not wholly impartial authorities).
                  Today we had a potato salad in the Hotel Du Tilleuil in the square in Bussiere (rhyme
                  away) for starters, and purchased a potato pie from the baker for supper, all to
                  accompany the sausage and lentil stew. The Tilleul was doing Fish and Chips in
                  English. In Gueret Gare sncf, reached on my final day's reservation (see below),
                  the lady on the bookstall, from whom I purchased two postcards offering an
                  illustrated potato pie recipe, read them carefully and assured me that the recipe
                  was comme il faut, and if the pie was not, that would be faute of mine.</p>
               <p>Reserve-an-agglobus: instructions for use </p>
               <p>1. Get your host to ring the magic number. 2. And recharge his phone to have any
                  chance of perlocutionary effect. 3. By now it's their lunch break, so have lunch
                  then start again. 4. Potatoes again. 5. Say which stops you want to get on at and
                  go to, and about when. 6. How would 7.51am suit you sir? 7. Text confirms this
                  offer at their closing time (6pm). 8. Bus may run up to 5 minutes early. There's
                  an interesting problem here, why don't they just say 7.46am? They don't want you
                  to think they run late? 9. 9-seater minibus appears at 7.44, bearing a driver and
                  lady passenger picked up somewhere else. The schoolkids ignore, clearly waiting
                  for something else. 10. Scramble in back, pay driver one measly euro and receive
                  one-way ticket. 11. It's now 7.46 so we're off. 12. Try to maintain polite
                  three-party conversation with no breakfast. 14. Descend at requested destination,
                  in this case Guéret station, some 25 minutes later, exchanging ritual enchantés
                  with driver. 15. No breakfast here either. And it's off to complete the round tour
                  of Clermont Ferrand, skirted on south (Arvant) on way out, now skirted on north
                  (Riom) on return, but never entered. A 15-minute change at Riom finally found a
                  sandwich. At last!</p>
               <p>So many memories, perhaps the true theme of this trip, as Gordon has recognised.
                  Of my last time in Lyon, in the autumn of 2012, whither came from Bologna with
                  Laura Gavioli and Natacha Niemants to run a seminar for Veronique Traverso,
                  looking for presents in the presqu'ile: Daniela and I were just retiring and
                  dreaming of going to Mongolia on the trans-Siberian the following spring. Le Puy
                  en Velay, where I spent wintry days with Stefania 25 years back, then starting
                  from Langeac imitating Stevenson, staying in the monastery and going to vespers in
                  La Bastide. Revisiting the station of Brive Le Gaillarde, where I came to meet up
                  with Lou and Lilette following an ESSE conference in Bordeaux - they had come on
                  the express from Paris and we got to see the prehistoric cave paintings near the
                  capital of foie gras, now about 20 years ago? And potatoes. Memories of tortilla
                  in Cordova just three months ago, on my first attempt to write up a trip. And now
                  coming back to Lyon: I remember my father's enthusiasm in 1956, as we came up on
                  the Mistral to Paris and he was just so impressed by the constant 140km/h for mile
                  after mile, perhaps dreaming of the timetable he would write for the West Coast
                  main line when electrification was completed a few years later. And now I'm on the
                  way back to Modane, and the mechanical piano museum where Daniela and I went on
                  our way back from the lake of Annecy in 2013. They all seem good memories, like
                  the dream I had the other night in La Vergne. Life is rich. When I reach Modane,
                  I'll exploit the Hotel Le Commerce for wifi to post this and for the coffee they
                  owe me. Question: with all these fields of cattle, why is it impossible to find
                  fresh milk in this country? All bull(s)?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Kufstein-Nurnberg-Antwerp-Liserna (June 2015)</head>
            <div>
               <head>2015-06-25</head>
               <p>Day 1</p>
               <p>It's party time in Kufstein. The bridge across the river (Inn, i suppose) is
                  barred. No room in the inn today, for traffic at any rate. On every street corner
                  is a stage with associated tyrolese band in associated costume, i.e. silly hats,
                  bare knees and lederhosen. But then this is the place where they built a castle
                  with advanced 1860s gunnery specially to protect the new railway linking Innsbruck
                  and Munich which then fell down (the castle that is, or rather was). At least a
                  fifth of the audience too are dressed up to the nines down to the knees: many
                  robust ladies with multicoloured skirts and protruding bosoms, age 14 upwards.
                  Sauerkraut sausage and beer on the stands that make it all look like an austrian
                  festa dell'unità, where families consume various freshly fried objects -
                  crescentine with sauerkraut? - but it takes me half an hour to find a space to sit
                  without invading others'. Daniela would have liked it, or shall we say I would
                  have liked it with her? </p>
               <p>Starting a journey to leave Italy, there are various things not to do. Basically,
                  don't fix an appointment with the landlord, who takes a large cheque as you hand
                  over the keys to Daniela's flat and then find you have lost the keys to your own.
                  Probably in the flat to which you no longer have the keys. The landlord smilingly
                  departs by moped and you are left with all the associated pieces of paper and
                  nowhere to put them. A retreat to the local bar offers them a fortnight's
                  safekeeping. That and a much-needed coffee done, with a comfortable 40 minutes
                  left to catch your train, you discover the buses only run half-hourly on summer
                  saturdays, and ring for a taxi to be texted ten minutes later that none is
                  available. Feeling like Quixote on Rocinante, when the latter's feet have been
                  tied and Sancho has just relieved himself in the vicinity, at last a call to the
                  ineffable fabrizio in his not-too-distant abode procures an unexpected improvised
                  lift, ending with five minutes to stroll past the police on the platform rounding
                  up suspiciously coloured would-be passengers - this train will cross borders! Two
                  ticket inspectors appear within five minutes of each other, and then it's lunch in
                  the restaurant car, a luxury of this austrian train, with meatballs and mash,
                  salad and grune veltliner, in the attempt to forget how much the landlord has just
                  done me for.</p>
               <p>The good news is Luciana, a student of Daniela's in the eighties, now teaching
                  Italian at Duke University (now there's a nice short address, luciana@duke.edu)
                  who is on her way to Trento and accosts me as I conclude a second lengthy and
                  abortive call to the electricity company in the vain attempt to close down
                  Daniela's account, seemingly impossible without production of both a death
                  certificate and an heir apparent in the company offices. Neither of which is
                  possible on a train heading up the Adige to the Brenner, reaching which I observe
                  two suspiciously coloured would-be passengers dash across the platform from the
                  loo to the train, while the assembled mass police forces of Italy and Austria are
                  all looking the other way.</p>
               <p>Day 2</p>
               <p>The Schwaenlein Gasthof at Nurnberg has a lot of things going for it. One: it is
                  astonishingly cheap, €30 a night (ok, the shower and toilet are on the other side
                  of the corridor). Two: it is quiet. Three: it is in the centre of town and only
                  three minutes' walk from the station. Four: it is one minute from the main drag.
                  Five: It has a little garden which looks up at a tower on the city wall, full of
                  garden furniture and plastic ducks and colourful flowers and what looks like a
                  stone hedgehog but with free wifi, where you can sit and drink beer/eat goulash
                  and consider how the day has been. And write up an instalment. Even if there are
                  cross-cultural communication problems with the calendar: they wrote to me asking
                  why I hadn't turned up on May 29, I wrote back saying I meant June 29, and of
                  course today is June 28. The landlady is suspicious; payment demanded in cash in
                  advance. </p>
               <p>How did we get here? The 8am train from Kufstein to Munich was a splendid Stadler
                  multiple unit, with table, power point, and blonde ticket inspector clutching a
                  magazine called HAPPINEZ. A cube containing a toilet placed conveniently in the
                  centre of each coach, so the entire coachload of passengers can monitor your exits
                  and entrances, marked by convenient red lights. And yes I could use my allbavaria
                  ticket all day on any train, including the munich underground. But I walked to the
                  Alte Pinakotek all the same, was offered a cigarette by one of the cleaning ladies
                  while waiting for it to open, and duly paid my euro sunday reduced rate admission.
                  Brueghel beckons, rapidly found in the shape of the Land of Cockaigne and the Head
                  of an Old Peasant Woman. In the former much is surreal: the roast pig with a
                  missing slice and a knife lodged in its skin running down the bank; the goose
                  whose head is curled up in the plate but not its body which seems mobile; the
                  background fence of sausages; the dancing egg in the foreground; and, we are told,
                  the (?roast) bird flying directly into the open mouth of the soldier in the
                  cake-tiled hut, before a clumsy 19th century restorer painted it eternally out.
                  The central figures bursting at the seams/laces, legs astride or together, forming
                  geometrical patterns with the sticks/lance of diagonals horizontals and verticals
                  across the canvas. Everything carefully positioned. What it all represents as an
                  allegory, heaven knows. Oh, and the man with the spoon emerging head down from a
                  cloud (of soup?) in an apparently knickerless state. As for the Old Peasant Woman,
                  she has an extraordinary nose, protruding excessively above her gaping mouth. Is
                  she too hoping for cockaigne? </p>
               <p>The first thing you see (or at any rate I saw) coming in on the train to Nurnberg
                  is Guy's Weinhaus. To be explored tomorrow, along with the Palace of Justice, home
                  of the trials and the birthplace of simultaneous interpreting, or so they say.
                  Goulasch and Knodel being over, all i need is bed. All my trials soon be over?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-06-30</head>
               <p>Day 3</p>
               <p>On one of the islands in the river at Nurnberg is a gate leading to The Hangman's
                  Museum. This is highly appropriate insofar as the Nuremberg trials concluded with
                  sentences of being hung rather than shot, which those found guilty would have
                  apparently preferred. The Memorium (sic) consists of numerous display panels in
                  German, with an audioguide in English. Me, two Chinese, and an American couple in
                  their seventies queue for the opening with the following dialogue: </p>
               <p>Me: Where are you from? </p>
               <p>Man:Las Vegas Nevada. And you?</p>
               <p>Me: England</p>
               <p>Man: Where's that? </p>
               <p>Disappointingly, all the sound clips from the trial seem to have had new
                  interpreting tracks added, so you don't get to hear the original interpreters
                  getting their knickers in. There were over 350 staff in the translation and
                  interpreting sections set up for the trials, dealing with four languages. And, it
                  would seem, a lot of cross-checking. The interpreters worked in pairs in each
                  booth: the second interpreter being there to listen and take over if and when the
                  first cracked up. While all the originals were recorded, it is not clear whether
                  the interpretations also were. Simultaneous interpreting was chosen as a means of
                  saving time compared with consecutive, thereby (it is claimed) giving those
                  interrogated less time to think before having to produce an answer. Or at any rate
                  not to privilege those who understood something of the source language. There is a
                  vast listing of subsequent post-war trials, leading up to the tribunal in The
                  Hague. All pretty depressing. And why did they restore the courtroom to its
                  original structure in 1987 as a memorial, but subsequently turn it back into a
                  standard courtroom on the current model for everyday use?</p>
               <p>The tourist office provides a map, most effective once you realise that the large
                  blowup of the city centre shows the centre of Furth rather than that of Nurnberg.
                  And leaflets illustrating events at the other two museums on the list for
                  tomorrow. The Nationalmuseum contains no Brueghels but several Cranachs (the
                  elder), a mixture of naked Venuses and of portraits of Martin Luther. And the DB
                  (Deutsche Bundesbahn) Museum - what more can I say, how can I miss that. </p>
               <p>Lunch again in the gasthof biergarten, of which I have found a pic, <ref
                     target="http://www.hotelguide.de/photos/38827307.jpg?fbclid=IwAR0b5nXZCGa9dP796vrgm7fcOZC1GHXcHGFGhyhYqMvgQ_l9ypE555Ze2f0"
                     >http://www.hotelguide.de/photos/38827307.jpg</ref>
               </p>
               <p>with fried objects, apple sauce, and the inevitable beer which turns into two.
                  Duly counted by two lines drawn by the waitress on my beermat. The condiments are
                  in the same glass containers you can find anywhere, only that they have convenient
                  sticky labels saying Salt and Pepper on the outside, should you have doubts or be
                  p*ssed out of your mind. A snooze, followed by a search for the post office and
                  stamps. Not made easy by the fact that most of the streets in this town are called
                  Lorenz something (strasse, platz, gasse ecc.), as is a large church. Appropriate
                  however, given that I have a date tomorrow for lunch with Gunter Lorenz, one of
                  the few people who makes me feel small, and who currently works in nearby Erlangen
                  - a little bit further than Furth - running the largest language centre in the
                  country, apparently. Size, size.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Day 4</head>
               <p>"So, lunch followed by a walk through town, possibly to Germanisches
                  Nationalmuseum, followed by hot/cold beverage and slight répas? In which case I
                  would suggest we meet up at 'Bar Celona' around 1.30? (It's by the river east of
                  the pedestrian bridge, everyone in the town centre knows it.)"</p>
               <p>So reads the morning mail from Herr Doctor Lorenz. This has two important
                  consequences. (a) I have no excuse not to spend the morning working on my paper
                  for Paris next week, since the Nationalmuseum is now scheduled for the afternoon.
                  (b) I duly turn up outside the Bar Celona at 1.30 looking for someone larger. A
                  text arrives announcing that he is at a table on the riverside. I duly do the
                  rounds of riverside tables, look to see if any other candidates for that label,
                  and find ja no gunter. Finally I inquire of the waitress. Ah, there is another Bar
                  Celona, a few hundred yards upriver, next to another footbridge. I text Gunter
                  accusing him of gross ambiguity and set off. It turns out to be a much nicer bar,
                  so he deserves credit for that. </p>
               <p>Chat about this and that, about me/you/him/her, a beer and a shandy, Gunter has a
                  pizza (the bar is Spanish), I a veggy omelette after all the pork steaks of the
                  previous day. As well as running the language centre in Erlangen, G now teaches
                  English phonetics, which I can imagine him good at, and explains to me various
                  curiosities of the German civil service which I shall not bore you with. Better to
                  move on to Cranach, of whom the Nationalmuseum has about 20 paintings and 20
                  prints, including as preannounced several of martin luther and two of the naked
                  venus and cupid, the latter of whom is in each case holding a piece of honeycomb
                  and in the process of being stung by various bees. There are apparently various
                  morals here, i.e. (a) that when stealing honeycomb you should keep your clothes on
                  (unless you are venus, who the bees don't seem to go for), and (b) that lusting
                  after the local venus (who is quite a little honey) may be risky. Cranach is
                  heavily into morals. Nearby, the Ill-matched couple shows a leering old man and a
                  far-from-innocent young lady whose hand is placed on an area of his anatomy which
                  has been discreetly excluded from the poster of the special exhibition. Her fancy
                  headgear suggests she many be in it for the money. Another painting, La bocca
                  della verità, shows a young lady placing her hand in a lion's mouth, watched by
                  observers of both sexes. This is apparently a test of whether she is telling the
                  truth about her marital fidelity. As the lion fails to bite, this demonstrates
                  that she has told the truth in claiming that she has only been touched by her
                  husband, and of course by the motley fool who has just put his arm round her waist
                  in the picture (of course actually being her lover in disguise). This is
                  apparently part of a series entitled Wiles of women. Cranach's morals seem pretty
                  flexible - so why all the Luthers, in various guises, or was he just hedging his
                  bets?</p>
               <p>Gunter seems well, tells me about his wife and children. The former has apparently
                  just jammed her school's colour printer, in the process - for the first time in
                  her life - of using it for a private purpose. She is apparently overcome with
                  shame, Gunter with laughter. Cranach would clearly have made something of this. </p>
               <p>On the subject of theft in Nuremberg and environs, we visit a shop going under the
                  name of The British Empire which sells marmite at 9 euros a jar. I don't
                  understand how, but Gunter manages to get a demonstration of dancing from one of
                  the assistants, to the chant of "1-2-3-4 oi". Gunter then retreats home, as we vow
                  undying mutual affection, and he threatens to invite me to give a talk in
                  Erlangen, I threaten to welcome them in Vergato en famille, etcetera. He also gets
                  a passer-by to take our joint photograph (the last one was taken in Graz with
                  Henry Widdowson), which he will send me so that I can continue to feel small.</p>
               <p>Most of Nuremberg got bombed, given its associations, but there is one street
                  which more or less survived, peopled by elderly ladies doing drawings of its
                  buildings. I wander along, up past another rebuilt church, and then down back to
                  the Gasthof, where I end up talking with a couple from Leipzig en route to
                  holidays in Austria with their baby Lorelei, and discussing Brueghel and Cranach
                  (she is an art historian), East-West sentiments in Germany, attitudes to Tsipras,
                  Merkel's incapacity to make decisions etc, over yet another beer, and so to bed.
                  But first, check mail: aargh! the channel tunnel is closed, says my Eurostar
                  consultant, no thanks to striking french ferryworkers. Eurostar says it is
                  reopening only a partial service. So where do we go from here? BED INDEED.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-07-04</head>
               <p>Day 5</p>
               <p>And it's farewell to the gasthof schwaenlein, which gunter yesterday explained to
                  me is in the heart of the redlight district, but nothing much did I see, at most a
                  slightly pink memorial to the tram shelter where gays met in the 1930s. But I'm
                  heading to the DB museum, behind the opera house, and where you get a reduction if
                  you show a train ticket. It's an impressive museum, historically ordered so that
                  the Adler, the repeatedly reconstructed working yellow locomotive on the first
                  line in Germany, Nurenberg-Furth (1835), comes after an illustrated account of
                  Trevethick, Stephenson, and the Rocket. </p>
               <p>Other highlights include a bit of the Flying Hamburger (which averaged 77mph from
                  Hamburg to Berlin in the 1930s)</p>
               <p>
                  <ref
                     target="https://l.facebook.com/l.php?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.winrail.com%2Fgallery%2520photos%2FFlying%2520Hamburger.jpg%3Ffbclid%3DIwAR3fuolo4_cx1iNkq274fxf8TKRwDsSzRkSXJ6Tivmjw0Sryk1njo40IHCk&amp;h=AT0-yBVvkCEl_MXyw6njUtAx5QI9K_pJTOe-hPoJNhh6OcFf0m38CR5hJB3Q21kjLrHH2D2m2R2iCNZ_qJLHdz8yj8Sfj38PovbjQIDKMDzOHze3rCVv0NnxS6XUFxVydKL32a4kmRNcP_eNb9sO7BmRczbCgsexBYDK"
                     >http://www.winrail.com/gallery%20pho…/Flying%20Hamburger.jpg</ref>
               </p>
               <p>and the Schienenzeppelin, a railcar with a propeller on its rear which apparently
                  reached 143mph in the same period, not to mention depressing documentation of the
                  capacity of trains to concentration camps - 5000 people!</p>
               <p>I enquire at the station information desk who say that as they can book tickets on
                  eurostar, the tunnel must be open, and go and discover coach 29 on the 11am ICE.
                  My reserved seat 71 is to be avoided as windowless, but fortunately others are
                  empty. Train late, rapid change at Frankfurt; next train late, rapid change at
                  Koeln; next train late (with lengthy deviation on way to Aachen) and so less time
                  to wait in the eurostar lounge (sic) in Brussels. The only notable events are: (a)
                  sitting behind the clear glass panel separating the front seats from the driver on
                  the quite dramatically winding new highspeed line from Frankfurt airport to Koeln;
                  (b) lunch in the restaurant car from Koeln to Aachen with a manufacturer of
                  milking machines for which the cows queue up of their own accord and with an
                  Egyptian lady living in Berlin who is going to an EU meeting in Brussels and
                  wonders what else one can do there (she expresses no interest in Brueghel or
                  Matisse, or indeed in the Mannekin Pis, so am rapidly stumped for suggestions);
                  (c) the gent at the opposite table in the eurostar who imports coffee from Antwerp
                  which is stuck in the lorry queue caused by the Striking French (sic - this is
                  also the name of the white wine opened for lunch in Oxford two days later).
                  Paddington with ten minutes to spare, buy a ticket from a friendly ticket clerk
                  who is helpfully standing next to the ticket machine on the bridge, and then await
                  train which is late because of a trespasser at Stroud, gets later due to work on
                  the relief lines to Didcot, and so finally on to Bath, where Fi is waiting to
                  whisk me and her violin to Wells in her new purple vehicle.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2015-07-28</head>
               <p> The return</p>
               <p>10 minutes walk from my lodgings (selected for that reason) via a third rate
                  espresso macchiato takes me to purchase a snowglobe of Big Ben for Sabrina and to
                  the queue for the 8.58 Eurostar to Brussels, where I am surrounded by a group of
                  35 (predominantly female) who are on a Great Railway Journey to the Baltic States,
                  and Eurostar apologetically only provide coffee after we emerge from the tunnel. I
                  skim through Wikipedia's list of Flemish proverbs in preparation for the day's
                  trip to Antwerp, and listen to the staff talking Italian between themselves. A
                  beautiful morning after a day of solid rain (shouldn't that be liquid?) in the
                  London wetlands. But by Antwerp it is of course pouring again, and the Meir is a
                  tunnel of soaking misery beneath the inverted digital humanities white umbrella
                  Lou lent me the day before. There's a moral here somewhere. Why Antwerp? Brueghels
                  of course, of which the Mayer van den Bergh Museum, essentially a plush private
                  house of a hundred years ago, contains two (as well as various of his children's
                  imitations). The first, known as Twelve Proverbs, is really a collection of
                  (twelve) beer mats, subsequently framed as a single whole. Each one illustrates a
                  proverb, the most popular being Pissing at the Moon - a rear view of a stout
                  flemish gentleman aiming at the crescent. Apparently a warning against
                  overreaching yourself. Fair enough. Perhaps I am trying to do too much too fast on
                  this journey, and crossing Germany in a single day, mainly on trains which stop
                  everywhere, is going to be excessive. We shall see.</p>
               <p>But the key proverb on this visit is not included in these twelve. ‘She could
                  plunder in front of hell and return unscathed’ is, say the books, a reference to
                  women's wiles and effrontery, embodied by Dulle Griet, or Mad Meg, who occupies
                  the centre of a wall behind a railing placed just too far away to enable you to
                  reach it and examine all the minor detail. But this is some painting, a vast
                  miscellany of forgotten allusions. Meg herself, slightly left of centre, is
                  looking into the mouth of hell - a real mouth with teeth, surmounted by nostrils
                  and eyes - the left one of which is partly hidden behind a Brueghelian tree. The
                  face is built in to the rockface. Meg is wearing a helmet and breastplate and
                  pointing a sword towards the train of small devils emerging from hell's mouth -
                  Boschian animalesque creatures who are much less threatening than Meg herself is.
                  She is carrying a moneychest under her arm, has a large cooking spoon sticking out
                  from her basket (stuffed with goodies), and from the waist down is clearly female
                  in skirt and black stockings. But that's far from all. Behind Meg is a near-mirror
                  image in form, this time inhabited by a tribe of women who are doing unspeakable
                  things to men-like devils, or devil-like men, who are emerging from the mouth of
                  the moat below a building, apparently men in full armour, but who when stripped
                  are devil-like. There is a lighted window in the wall of the building above them,
                  where two heads and a beaker can be seen, a window which corresponds to Satan's
                  eye in the face of hell. And if you look back at Satan's other eye, the one
                  half-hidden behind the tree, you can see that its colour is the same as that of
                  the lighted window, and indeed that it has the grating pattern of glasswork - so
                  which of the two gates is that of hell, one, both, or neither? Could the men in
                  armour be a reference to the Spanish invasion - and in this case should we
                  interpret the whole as a call to resist the invaders? Or simply to resist greedy
                  women (Gold diggers of 1562)? Is is it significant that Dulle Griet was also the
                  name of a cannon set up by Philip of Burgundy at the siege of Ghent a century
                  earlier? </p>
               <p>But there are many other things. The women are surmounted by a figure whose
                  exposed bum is shitting coins which some of them are collecting. He holds a large
                  boat on his shoulder - a merchant of Antwerp? - and his extended naked foot is at
                  the exact centre of the composition. Above Meg herself is a small seascape, with
                  an island on which sit two naked figures - Adam and Eve? And as always (?) in
                  Brueghel there is geometry. In this case, as well as horizontal and vertical
                  lines, joining for example the eye, Meg's helmet and the window, there are two
                  clear diagonals from corner to corner which divide the painting into four
                  superimposed triangles: drawing a line from the top left to the bottom right,
                  beneath it we find the walls of the mouth of hell, Mad Meg, the devil-fixing women
                  facing towards us, above it the harp, adam and eve, the cash-crapper with his bum
                  and boat, the defending women facing away from us, the panful of soldiers above
                  and the invading army coming through the moat, with the blaze of yellow light from
                  the top right hand corner; while drawing a line from the bottom left to the top
                  right, below it we find Meg's skirt and basket, the crapper's bum, the women and
                  the army, while above it we find the boat and the armoured upper half of Meg
                  gazing into the mouth of hell - and interestingly, the light in the top right hand
                  corner only illuminates the bottom triangle. Almost a division between the human
                  and the superhuman which suggests analogies ... </p>
               <p>The train back from Antwerp - one of the most impressive stations in the world -
                  to Brussels is running an hour late due to flooding in Holland, so I go to Leuven
                  instead and change, which takes only nearly as long, before a five minute steep
                  climb from the back entrance of Brussels Nord to the Hotel Albert, cheap but not
                  unduly squalid. For dinner they recommend the next road parallel in the Turkish
                  quarter, where I duly sample a tasty Turkish Pizza with no alcohol.</p>
               <p>And so to bed, and a terrible coffee while waiting for the near-empty 6.33 ICE to
                  Frankfurt, which provides scrambled eggs for breakfast (not recommended - next
                  time try the Belgian waffle) and a newspaper at Cologne, after a diversion via
                  near Dusseldorf. Make my connection to Wurzburg via 50 metres of
                  evil-stale-piss-smelling subway at Frankfurt, watch and hear the refreshments
                  trolley negotiate the stairs on the double-deck train, and thence connection to
                  Treuchtlingen. Where? Have I ever been on the line to Treuchtlingen before? No.
                  And would I again? Probably not. Where did I start my journey that day? Brussels.
                  And will end it? In Kufstein, just over the frontier with Austria. On what kind of
                  ticket? A lovely weekender. The young lady who is interviewing me studies
                  psychology in Wurzburg, earning vacation cash from the regional railway authority,
                  and deduces I am out of my mind to be taking a route which includes over 60
                  intermediate station stops. She and her partner wave goodbye in Treuchtlingen,
                  where they tell me there is a locomotive on display, but as I only have a
                  four-minute connection for Munich, the locomotive will have to wait the next
                  (improbable) time. And then on to Munich via Augsburg, then from Munich to
                  Kufstein after the halfmile walk to platform 9, with a horde of running screaming
                  small children on the train. But that's ok, there is an organ recital being aired
                  to the entire population as I walk over the bridge to the Auracher Loechl, who
                  offer a (small) glass of prosecco upon arrival. To be followed an austrian
                  meat-potato-kren dinner outside. And a beer to conclude before bed. </p>
               <p>In the morning it is of course pouring once again, compensated partly by a vast
                  array of goodies at the buffet breakfast ranging from stuffed apricots to fresh
                  butter to Austrian lard (sic) and seven types of bread - as well as tepid
                  scrambled eggs which only bring back sad memories of Deutsche Bahn. The postoffice
                  opens at 8, produces stamps, and then it's back to the station for the 0841 to
                  Bologna. Which is full of howling children in 1st class, making careful study of
                  the reservations necessary to identify a seat which will be free from Innsbruck
                  and offers a table and space in a 4-seat compartment. All I now have to do is
                  write up this blog and wait for the restaurant car to serve lunch around Trento.
                  Such is life. But next time, be in less of a hurry. And possibly do without the
                  large head and stem of fresh garlic from the sussex cliffs sticking out of the
                  pocket of your bag.</p>
               <p>Ah, but you thought it was all over. Train broke down at Fortezza/Franzensfeste.
                  500 people attempt to board a local train which holds 150. I go for a walk and a
                  pre-lunch aperitif while waiting for the next Munich-Bologna train. Which is then
                  duly announced as having a delay of 2 hours and a half. So a glance at the remains
                  of the roman road, perhaps the most reliable means of transport round these parts,
                  and a number of SAD and Trenitalia local trains (whose cost Deutsche Bahn will
                  pay?) end up getting me to Bologna four hours late along with an interesting
                  collection of: a young German who is settling the remains of the war in Cote
                  d'Ivoire; a Bremen blonde sweetie heading for Venice; a pianist from near Macerata
                  who lives in Munich and has got to play on the same piano as Robert Schumann in
                  Bonn; five interrailing 19-year-old girls from Madrid who are en route from Vienna
                  to Rome via Bologna. So maybe second class has advantages, at least in the short
                  term, in terms of the company. Farewell, as I just make the train to Vergato and
                  call up my taxidriver. Liserna it is, again. Farewell for now.</p>
            </div>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>Liserna- Berlin - London (March 2016) </head>
            <div>
               <head>2016-03-18</head>
               <p> Back to Bach (Partoneofanotherguytravelblog).</p>
               <p>Day one</p>
               <p>My neighbour Michela gives me a lift through the rain down the hill to the
                  station, and a ticket to Bologna which for some reason she has in her pocket as
                  well as her season ticket. She is going to a meeting to discuss the problems of
                  the local adolescents, who are apparently pissed off at not being represented at
                  this meeting. The train is appropriately filled with howling adolescents on way
                  home from school. An hour to wait in Bologna for the EuroCity, where I run into an
                  ex-student who is now a freelance interpreter, heading for Trieste to see her
                  boyfriend, We exchange pleasantries about the state of the market, and there is a
                  not-so-subtle satisfaction in saying I have a first-class ticket to Berlin in my
                  pocket. Another ex-student waves to me in the street, but is clearly in a hurry,
                  alas. Now I have a compartment to myself for next five hours. One of the most
                  comfortable trains I know: black leather with four reclining seats, assorted
                  tables, and a waiter who appears from the restaurant car and brings Austrian food
                  and beer with real crockery to your seat from time to time. Power, reading lights,
                  turn down the loudspeaker volume, and no wi-fi to distract from perusing the
                  snow-capped Dolomites and Elliot Gardiner's chapter on The Great Passion.</p>
               <p>Destination Bach (via Breughel). Culminating in the St Matthew Passion at the
                  Barbican next Saturday. Gardiner explains the antiphonal structure of the work,
                  designed for three choirs and two instrumental ensembles scattered around the
                  Thomaskirche in Leipzig, and the respective functions of recitative (story
                  telling), aria (emotional reaction), and chorale (public response, based on
                  well-known hymns). It is and isn't a tragic opera, he argues. </p>
               <p>Watch the dusk fall on a mainly grey sky as we pause at Fortezza, bringing back
                  vivid visual memories of the roman road explored when the train broke down here
                  one summer (this same train in the other direction). Triggered memories bring back
                  contextual features which are different from the trigger stimulus, such as the
                  summer light in contrast to wintry gloom. Now there is thick snow at the Brenner
                  pass, where I descend to stretch legs along with the waiter and his mate. Station
                  deserted apart from two middle-eastern youths who emerge from the disabled toilet
                  on the platform, ask for a cigarette in otherwise incomprehensible English, and
                  reimmerge into the disabled toilet to smoke same. The papers say that Austria has
                  ceased to observe Schengen, and indeed here they are observing nothing at all: to
                  jump on the train would have been no problem. </p>
               <p>Tonight's destination is Flints_Bach (note the large numbers of places as well as
                  composers called something Bach). My traditional frontier stopover point, the gin
                  palace in Kufstein (aka Auracher Loechl), is sadly closed for replumbing, as a
                  between-trains wander around the deserted town between trains confirms. Kufstein
                  has a noticeable police presence, and my passport is demanded as I board the local
                  into Germany. Could I be a refugee Austrian? It is late, and at FlintsBach the
                  only open door to the Gasthof Falkenstein leads through the kitchens, appropriate
                  insofar as the hotel is also a butchery famed for its wurst. Of which more
                  tomorrow. Will I too be butchered? My room seems designed as a stable. Two wooden
                  bunks with ladders and lattices, and a glass-sided manger filled with hay. Will
                  they play me the Christmas Oratorio as a wake-up call?</p>
               <p>Day two</p>
               <p>The wurst breakfast is on Fridays. Today is Thursday. Ergo sum = no chance to beat
                  the purported record of twenty-three in the all the wurst you can eat for
                  breakfast competition. Have to make do with some rather good smoked ham and rather
                  nasty pseudo-Brie. In compensation, the basket at reception where you would expect
                  to find nasty little sweets instead contains a range of small individually priced
                  pieces of ham (and wurst). Two euros seventy-two cents of wurst as a souvenir,
                  counted out to the last cent. We are in Bavaria, Auf wiedersehen and next time
                  make it Friday. It's a beautiful morning on the snow-capped Bavarian alps as we
                  head up to Muenchen. A 3D postcard of Ludwig and Neuschwanstein seems to sum it
                  all up.</p>
               <p>Back to Breugel/Breughel/Bruegel/Brueghel - the delights of watching others
                  misspell your name and changing the way you spell it yourself in order to breed
                  further confusion. Destination tomorrow: the Flemish proverbs, said to be 112 in
                  number, largely copied from Erasmus and all depicted on one large canvas at the
                  Berlin Gemaldegalerie which has more to it than an empty herring. All listed on
                  Wikipedia (with illustrations). The gent sitting opposite me has finished the
                  Sudoku in Die Welt well before me: one should never yawn against the oven,
                  particularly after too little sleep.</p>
               <p>But lunch with big G, who suddenly towered over me as I sat on the park bench
                  staring at his least favourite statue, made up for robustly with a portion of
                  eight Nuremberg sausages and kraut, all washed down with the necessary beer.
                  Toasts drunk to the tune of another saying, decidedly German rather than Flemish,
                  and which is too rude to report in those details which concern
                  anatomical/functional analogies between ladies and beer glasses. Before, a
                  beautiful sunny day to wander round the botanical gardens and hunt unsuccessfully
                  for that rarest of establishments in today's Germany, namely a post office. Good
                  practice in asking for and deciphering directions, but else to no avail. Big G is
                  convinced of the virtue of repetition in language learning, getting his students
                  to listen to an episode of Just a Minute from beginning to end without stopping,
                  and to do this every day until they have understood it all (requiring on average
                  10 listenings of the same episode) - and then move on to the next episode and do
                  the same thing. If you can manage Just a minute you can manage nearly anything?
                  There must be a Flemish proverb for this: The meat on the spit must be basted?</p>
               <p>Today is a lot of trains (six at the last count). Have finally got a ticket
                  inspector to show me where the power points are on old ICEs (this brings us back
                  to anatomical/functional analogies again). This is the last train of the day,
                  destination Berlin Hauptbahnhof. The last time I passed through Braunschweig was
                  getting off and back onto the train for East German passport and customs control
                  in the middle of the night, which took about two hours. Things have clearly
                  changed: now a one minute stop. The hotel Meininger Hauptbahnhof is, as its name
                  might suggest, immediately outside the main entrance to Berlin Hauptbahnhof,
                  opposite a taxi rank populated by police cars. The dog is in the pot. So be it.
                  Goodnight.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>2016–03-22</head>
               <p>Days three and four</p>
               <p>It's not as easy as it might seem to see the Flemish Proverbs. There are about 120
                  different proverbs, and the guided tours of the Gemaeldegalerie clearly enjoy
                  pointing out different proverbs to parties of elderly German ladies, not least the
                  large lady in red who is placing a blue cloak on her elderly husband whom she has
                  apparently cuckolded. I have yet to find a convincing account of the symbolism of
                  colours in Brueghel, only suggestions about a distinction between stupidity and
                  vice - but little certainty as to which colour represents which, and there hardly
                  seems to be a clear dividing line. Being a highlight of the guided tour, on my
                  first morning in Berlin the same guide appeared thrice with different flocks who
                  all sat down on their portable collapsible chairs and made the painting invisible
                  to anyone else for half an hour. So had to resort to the other Brueghel, just next
                  to it, which nobody was looking at (see below) - or else console myself with the
                  naked lovelies of the elder Cranach next door - including an extraordinary one
                  where elderly ladies strip and immerge themselves in a lake from which they emerge
                  rejuvenated on the other side - or with the two Verneers located in the opposite
                  direction, and their shiny objects - a wine glass, and a pearl necklace. </p>
               <p>Not all the proverbs depicted by B are as self-explanatory as "he who eats fire
                  shits sparks", and many are only just visible because of dark or distance,
                  requiring detailed study from close up. </p>
               <p>What many details do is document other Breughels. For instance, on the horizon,
                  The Blind leading the Blind. The same subject as in the later Naples picture.
                  Beyond the column of the blind men is a church steeple, again as in Naples, and
                  another proverbial reference: "The journey is not yet over when one can discern
                  the church and steeple". Doubly so if you are sightless and falling into a
                  ditch.Again on the horizon, a gentleman is crapping beneath a gallows ("being
                  undeterred"). There's a similar scene in the later Magpie on the Gallows at
                  Darmstadt. What strikes me most is that there appear to be two birds (size about 2
                  millimetres each) sitting on the gallows - presumably magpies, as in the Darmstadt
                  painting. This doesn't seem to correspond to a proverb - unless there is really a
                  "get yourself hung and magpies will pluck out your eyes"? Need to check Erasmus,
                  the recognised authority on the subject, having collected 3000-odd sayings. </p>
               <p>So Flemish Provers is an extraordinary work for its ability to cast light on other
                  Brueghel paintings - and drawings, eg the famous "Big fish eat little fish", of
                  which there is a miniature here. There's a lot of wry humour too: the man
                  confessing to the devil ("don't tell your enemy your secrets") shows a devil who
                  looks extremely bored. Sixth and lastly is the lady who keeps the hen's egg and
                  lets the goose's egg go ("make a bad choice"). Only the goose's egg has legs and
                  is running down the roof - an idea repeated in the half-eaten running egg at the
                  centre of the Munich Land of Cockaigne. In which, like here, there is also a pig
                  with a carving knife slipped through its skin - probably in illustration of "The
                  pig is stabbed through the belly" - i.e. "it's a foregone conclusion".</p>
               <p>There are dogs, pigs, sheep, oxen, fish, birds, a stork, hens, and geese in the
                  proverbs - I particularly identified with the bespectacled individual busy
                  surveying three large hens (?"don't count your chickens before they're hatched"?)
                  - but as far as I can see no monkeys. An absence which makes yet more enigmatic
                  the other Brueghel painting in the Gemaeldegalerie, generally known as The Two
                  Monkeys, Almost the only Brueghel painting without any human figures. And very
                  alarming too. It's a tiny picture, about a foot square, and it's a matter of
                  pictures within pictures. Working outwards from the centre and rear, we have a
                  backdrop of the river and town of Antwerp, with miscellaneous boats and steeples
                  respectively - and of course two birds flying above. This view is framed by an
                  arch under which the two monkeys are sitting, who are chained to a ring placed at
                  its centre. Lastly we have the outside of the arch, acting as a frame (including
                  Bruegel's signature and date) for the arch containing the monkeys and the view.
                  All this is placed within a wooden frame which itself provides a further three
                  frames within frames. </p>
               <p>The monkeys don't look happy. One is looking towards the viewer with wide sad
                  eyes, of the other, a little further back, we have a side view. He appears to be
                  looking down into the river. In front of this monkey are a few broken nutshells
                  lying on the floor of the arch, suggesting they may be hungry. It seems usually to
                  be suggested that they have sold their freedom for a mess of porridge, perhaps
                  also matching the Flemish proverb "Go to court for a hazel nut" (must check
                  Erasmus on this one too). Since the monkeys appear to be on desolation row, this
                  leads to reinterpret the background view. Is the ship behind the ring bringing
                  nuts for their relief? Or is the trade world of Antwerp merely a repetition of the
                  monkeys' imprisonment, itself a victim of avarice? And what, oh what, are those
                  two birds doing in the sky?</p>
               <p>Thinking I may never come back here (I didn't like Berlin, not helped by an
                  unccoperative hotel who couldn't even manage a wakeup call, or by the only place I
                  could find for lunch being the Microsoft Digital Eatery in Unter den Linden), I
                  went back to the Brueghels the next day for another look, after a quick visit to
                  the gates of Babylon on the museum island in the east. Could start again on the
                  Brueghels - the attendant asked me if I liked them - but won't. Afterwards, queued
                  for a returned ticket at the Philharmonie in von Karajan strasse in the hope of
                  hearing Barenboim do Mahler 9, preceded by an engineer pianist from Milan, then
                  collectively drowned our disappointment in small beer. But he did tell me where to
                  buy an electric piano, and said he would let me know how to get into La Scala
                  dress rehearsals. And was duly impressed when I told him about Bach. He then went
                  off to an alternative Sibelius concert, in the Hauptbahnhof I bought a roll for
                  dinner to eat in my room, opting for an early night.</p>
               <p>And what was the highlight of Berlin-London in 11 hours? Undoubtedly Cologne
                  cathedral, which I had never entered before and where I had half an hour between
                  trains. To be revisited at any opportunity. Why on earth has Gothic come to denote
                  horror? </p>
               <p>And thus into the UK, and what may happen here. But probably the right place to
                  end this travelblogue, staring into the sunset over the Channel.</p>

            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
