<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/home/lou/Public/TEIslides/teislides.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>September tour 2019</title>
                <author>Lou Burnard Consulting</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unpublished draft</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>born digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-10-21">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <!--Pending/20190913_102127.jpg-->
            <div type="slide">
                <head>13 September: Bristol </head>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://lb42.github.io/W/media/20190913_102330.jpg" width="650px"
                    />
                </figure>
                <p>Some boxes have been unpacked, and it's possible to live in Clifton Park Road.
                    But I have committments on the continent to enjoy, during these dying days of
                    free movement. So with a nod from Mr Maneki-Neko, I abandoned Lilette to do more
                    box work, and took the bus to Temple Meads, whence by Great Western and too many
                    underground trains (top tip, which I had forgotten, there are two underground
                    stations at Paddington: choosing the wrong one condemns you to an extra tedious
                    interchange at Edgware Road) via Liverpool Street and the Central Line to far
                    flung Stratford, arriving in time for tea, which I took in the horrible coffee
                    bar at the station exist, taking the opportunity to recharge my phone so that I
                    could let Elizabeth and Daphne know grand-pere was in town. </p>
                <p>It's only a short walk from Stratford station to their house, and worth the
                    effort. </p>

                <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://lb42.github.io/W/media/20190913_154418.jpg" width="650px"/>
                    <head>Daphne helps trundle my suitcase</head>
                </figure>
                <p>An agreeable evening in Maryland ensued, during which Daphne prepared a birthday card for her dad.
                </p>
            </div>
            <!--
Pending/20190913_145535.jpg
Pending/20190913_145616.jpg
Pending/20190913_151210.jpg
Pending/20190913_152114.jpg
Pending/20190913_153700.jpg
Pending/20190913_154130.jpg
Pending/20190913_154418.jpg
Pending/20190913_163835.jpg
Pending/20190913_163849.jpg
Pending/20190913_163853.jpg
Pending/20190913_163927.jpg
Pending/20190913_163947.jpg-->

            <div type="slide">
                <head>14 September: London to Munich</head>
                <p>An early start next morning, since the plan is to get the 1100 Eurostar
                    departure. Armed with my special spar-preise DB ticket von London nach Munchen
                    (price ??), I head back to Stratford International, so-called, even though no
                    international train has ever stopped here; nor are they likely to any time
                    soon, alas. The sun shines none the less, and the streetscape has its moments:</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://lb42.github.io/W/media/20190914_081829.jpg" width="650px"/>
                    <head>Major Road Ahead</head>
                </figure>
                <p>A commuter train from the wilds of East Anglia deposits me at St Pancras, and I
                    make my way through the usual processing to the Business Lounge, probably for
                    the last time for a while, since my carte blanche membership expires next month.
                    Farewell to free coffee, free nibbles, and (in Paris) free cocktails. Farewell
                    to a spot of calm before the journey and the sensation of being a member of a
                    bourgeois elite; I am no longer worthy, and unlikely to become so again any time
                    soon. The number of agencies willing to shell out for my train trips to France
                    is much reduced. Ah well, it was nice while it lasted. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://lb42.github.io/W/media/20190914_102351.jpg" width="400px"/>
                    <head>Farewell to all this</head>
                </figure>
                <p>But no matter, it's time for me and the hoards to board ES???, the 1110 departure for Brussells.
                  My reserved seat in the very end of the train. .</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://lb42.github.io/W/media/20190914_104651.jpg" width="400px"/>
                    <head>The tail end of my Eurostar</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The journey across Kent, under the channel, across Northern France, and into
                    Belgium is, of course, utterly unremarkable, just as we like it, and we pull
                    into Brussels Midi on time at . At which point I discover that my promised xxx
                    onward connexion to Munich has already left, half an hour earlier than
                    timetabled when I booked it. I remonstrate with a patient person in the Belgian ticket office,
                    who passes me on to a patient person in the German ticket office. Neither of
                    them can do anything practical other than propose a revised itinerary which,
                    with the best will in the world, will get me into Munich two hours later than
                    planned, precluding a pleasant Bavarian evening dinner. I therefore proceed out of the
                station into the street and seek some pleasant lunch instead, so as to make
                better use of the yawning two hour chasm into which the 
                anticipated modest 25 minute connexion time 
                has transformed itself.  
                </p><p>At least the train I am now catching is also retimed for engineering works. Off we go to
                Frankfurt on board ICE 215, retimed but otherwise as reliable and comfortable as ever. At Frankfurt
                I change onto another ICE train, heading south to München. And so to the Ibis Munchen City, for
                a good night's sleep, chosen mainly for its proximity to the station, though the fact that
                they always give me a free drink on arrival may also have encouraged me.  
               </p> <!-- My epic journey to #teiconf2019 hit its first bump... Brussels to Frankfurt trains 
                    retimed for engineering works, so that  what would have been a nice 25 min connexion 
                    id now a yawning 120 mins chasm. Oh well. Time for lunch.-->
                <!--                Now on board ice 215 to Frankfurt which also left 30 mins early. 
                    Engineering works.
                ust passing through köln a mere 2hourdlater than expected enrpute to
                #teiconf2019. Nice statue though.
                Last train of the day is ice759 to München today running in reverse 
                formation to confuse me en route 
                to #teiconf2019-->
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="https://lb42.github.io/W/media/timeline-09-14.png"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <!-- Pending/20190915_080317.jpg
Pending/20190915_080413.jpg
Pending/20190915_103053.jpg
Pending/20190915_111253.jpg
Pending/20190915_115523.jpg
Pending/20190915_115651.jpg
Pending/20190915_115824.jpg
Pending/20190915_115853.jpg
Pending/20190915_125048.jpg
Pending/20190915_125916.jpg
Pending/20190915_130704.jpg
Pending/20190915_132120.jpg
Pending/20190915_132134.jpg
Pending/20190915_135953.jpg
Pending/20190915_142843.jpg
Pending/20190915_142932.jpg
Pending/20190915_142938.jpg
Pending/20190915_150555.jpg
Pending/20190915_150754.jpg
Pending/20190915_150756.jpg
Pending/20190915_152057.jpg
Pending/20190915_155053.jpg
Pending/20190915_161039.jpg
Pending/20190915_161111.jpg
Pending/20190915_161113.jpg
Pending/20190915_182505.jpg
Pending/20190915_183311.jpg-->
            <div type="slide">
                <head>15 September : Munich to Graz </head>
                <p>Next morning, I dilly dally over breakfast, check out, and take a slow walk back to 
                    the station. Which was a mistake, since my onward train to Graz 
                    was also retimed to leave 30
                    minutes earlier than expected, i.e. just as I was strolling into the station. Curses. 
                    I remonstrate further with a DB person, and get lots of complicated reticketting.  
                    I re-assert control of my destiny by plotting
                    a slightly different route than they propose. It won't get me to Graz any sooner, but 
                    it means less hanging around Munich HBF on a boring morning. I get a 
                    metro ticket to Munich OstBahnhof, 
                    where I can catch the 1138 to Salzburg enjoy a 20 minute pause for refreshment, (an abstemious 
                    glass of mineral water on a sunny terrace) and then proceed on to 
                    Bischofshofen. From Bischofsen, I am delightfully surprised to learn, my train is a famous one with its own  
                    entry in Wikipedia, and a mega-scenic route across the alps, which is particularly nice since my re-ticketting
                    has placed me in the first class carriage with huge observational windows. The sun is shining
                    and the alpine scenery is indeed exceptionally, well, scenic. EC163: the Transalpin. 
            </p>
               <p>I arrive into Graz at 17h45, and take a taxi to my AirBNB, located in a pedestrian
                    street the other side of the park which separates Karl Franzen's magnificent
                    University from the rest of the city. Ah Austria: how civilised. My residence
                    for the next week is a bed-sit five minutes walk from the Uni, next door to a
                    Chinese restaurant, and handy for the Spar, as well as assorted restaurants. </p>
                <p>The TEI Conference 2019 duly unfolds, with or without my attention. I confess to feeling somewhat
                    alienated or excluded, though that is, of course, my own choice. After all this
                    time the TEI has to be able to get by without me very well, after all. I went to
                    one side meeting of the TEI Council where the long standing question of how to
                    introduce Standoff markup without totally screwing up the existing architecture
                    was thrashed out, or churned about, or generally pondered. I went to some good
                    sessions and some less good. The weather behaved impeccably and the sandwiches were irreproachable.
                    The opening plenary was notable because Jan
                    suggested that TEI might possibly have something to offer statistically minded
                    distant readers or stylometricians or whatever they are called this week.
                    However, nobody seemed to take this very seriously, nor did I find anyone who
                    wanted to go out for dinner with me. I spent many evenings arguing fruitlessly
                    with the appalling telephone banking service offered by Santander. On the whole,
                    and in retrospect, it was a rather depressing week.</p>            </div>
          <!--  Pending/20190916_092917.jpg
            Pending/20190916_093159.jpg
            Pending/20190916_094027.jpg
            Pending/20190916_104853.jpg
            Pending/20190916_104923.jpg
            Pending/20190916_104945.jpg
            Pending/20190916_125321.jpg
            Pending/20190917_103713.jpg
            Pending/20190917_103733.jpg
            Pending/20190917_142641.jpg
            Pending/20190917_143222.jpg
            Pending/20190917_161620.jpg
            Pending/20190917_161908.jpg
            Pending/20190917_161916.jpg
            Pending/20190917_161933.jpg
            Pending/20190917_164344.jpg
            Pending/20190917_170003.jpg
            Pending/20190917_170821.jpg
            Pending/20190917_171641.jpg
            Pending/20190917_175341.jpg
            Pending/20190917_175543.jpg
            Pending/20190917_175603.jpg
            Pending/20190917_175632.jpg
            Pending/20190918_093610.jpg
            Pending/20190918_093620.jpg
            Pending/20190918_093627.jpg
            Pending/20190918_093943.jpg
            Pending/20190918_093951.jpg
            Pending/20190918_094021.jpg
            Pending/20190919_120918.jpg
            Pending/20190919_165135.jpg
            Pending/20190919_192604.jpg
            Pending/20190920_110726.jpg
            Pending/20190920_110728.jpg
            Pending/20190920_110755.jpg
            Pending/20190920_110804.jpg
            Pending/20190920_110822.jpg
            Pending/20190920_111512.jpg
            Pending/20190920_111520.jpg
            Pending/20190920_124949.jpg
            Pending/20190920_125127.jpg
            Pending/20190920_130322.jpg
            Pending/20190920_131912.jpg
            Pending/20190920_131946.jpg
            Pending/20190920_131956.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132003.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132050.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132126.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132131.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132139.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132244.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132253.jpg
            Pending/20190920_132751.jpg
            Pending/20190920_133505.jpg
            Pending/20190920_133757.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134552.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134600.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134627.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134629.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134723.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134740.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134827.jpg
            Pending/20190920_134854.jpg
            Pending/20190920_135209.jpg
            Pending/20190920_163657.jpg
            Pending/20190920_165543.jpg
            Pending/20190920_165614.jpg
            Pending/20190920_165807.jpg
            
            --><div type="slide">
                <!--Pending/20190921_082849.jpg
Pending/20190921_090133.jpg
Pending/20190921_090400.jpg
Pending/20190921_090424.jpg
Pending/20190921_105510.jpg
Pending/20190921_105517.jpg
Pending/20190921_110742.jpg
Pending/20190921_110839.jpg
Pending/20190921_115441.jpg
Pending/20190921_120722.jpg
Pending/20190921_120730.jpg
Pending/20190921_120802.jpg
Pending/20190921_121515.jpg
Pending/20190921_121850.jpg
Pending/20190921_121854.jpg
Pending/20190921_124422.jpg
Pending/20190921_125831.jpg
Pending/20190921_125841.jpg
Pending/20190921_134941.jpg
Pending/20190921_135214.jpg
Pending/20190921_135345.jpg
Pending/20190921_135455.jpg
Pending/20190921_142757.jpg
Pending/20190921_143203.jpg
Pending/20190921_143346.jpg
Pending/20190921_144409.jpg
Pending/20190921_144427.jpg
Pending/20190921_144918.jpg
Pending/20190921_145051.jpg
Pending/20190921_145057.jpg
Pending/20190921_145141.jpg
Pending/20190921_145210.jpg
-->
                <head>September 21 : Graz - Szombethaly</head>
                <p>Casting off the dust of academic conferences, I took the 1108 departure from Graz
                    down to the Hungarian border, and a station called <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Szentgotth%C3%A1rd">Szentgotthárd</ref>, possibly the
                    same saint as he of the pass, possibly not. In any case, this was a most agreeable
                    journey, chuntering through the mountains and forests of lower Styria, with
                    their gingerbread-style cottages, rural farmyards, fields of maize and pumpkins
                    mostly now harvested for the winter. The train follows the route of a river,
                    which I am mildly amused to learn is known as the Raab. </p><p>At Saint Gotthard, I transfer to a waiting Hungarian train, which is a restful green colour,
                    which then continues down the river valley to the nearest town, which rejoices
                    in the name of Szombethaly, about which I know nothing, except that it was the
                    birthplace of (a) Saint Martin, according to ancient medieval tradition and  (b)
                    Leo Bloom's father, according to James Joyce. Arriving at 1915 I have time to
                    admire a rather fine baroque station, and to wander down a main street clearly
                    reconstructed quite recently, before checking into my allegedly boutique hotel
                    at ?. Bags dumped, I  sally forth in search of dinner. But who is this familiar
                    figure, turning his head to greet me half way down the main drag? How very
                    conceptual.   Dinner is decidedly Hungarian, being goulash and noodles, to the accompaniment of
                    loud and very annoying light music. </p><!--
Sep 21
Today's train is a little cutie... 1108 from Graz to the Hungarian border. Saint Gothard (a différent one) here we come!
                Now trundling through forests and mountains with gingerbread cottages to match. 
                Principal crops round here seem to be maize and pumpkins
                The last hour or so has been pootling along the valley of the raab .. but googlemaps now tells me we have crossed the Styrian border
                We're definitely not in Styria any more. The trains are green and people talk funny.
Image
-->

            </div>
    <!-- 
-->
            <!--Pending/20190922_080900.jpg
Pending/20190922_080925.jpg
Pending/20190922_081052.jpg
Pending/20190922_081828.jpg
Pending/20190922_081833.jpg
Pending/20190922_083118.jpg
Pending/20190922_083137.jpg
Pending/20190922_090150.jpg
Pending/20190922_090227.jpg
Pending/20190922_090237.jpg
Pending/20190922_090341.jpg
Pending/20190922_090544.jpg
Pending/20190922_090720.jpg
Pending/20190922_095957.jpg
Pending/20190922_101533.jpg
Pending/20190922_105913.jpg
Pending/20190922_111019.jpg
Pending/20190922_115007.jpg
Pending/20190922_115532.jpg
Pending/20190922_120910.jpg
Pending/20190922_120952.jpg
Pending/20190922_121249.jpg
Pending/20190922_121812.jpg
Pending/20190922_122815.jpg
Pending/20190922_122819.jpg
Pending/20190922_125927.jpg
Pending/20190922_125949.jpg
Pending/20190922_135433.jpg
Pending/20190922_135451.jpg
Pending/20190922_135709.jpg
Pending/20190922_135744.jpg
Pending/20190922_135852.jpg
Pending/20190922_162347.jpg-->
            
            <div type="slide">
                <head>September 22: Szombethaly - Budapest</head>
<p>I do have a little time to explore Szombethaly next morning, and the sun is shiuning in an attempt to encourage me.</p>
            </div>

            <!--Pending/20190923_104807.jpg
Pending/20190923_131021.jpg
Pending/20190923_140139.jpg
Pending/20190923_140208.jpg
Pending/20190923_140300.jpg
Pending/20190923_140304.jpg
Pending/20190924_062009.jpg
Pending/20190924_062017.jpg
Pending/20190924_153535.jpg
Pending/20190924_173346.jpg-->
            
            <!-- 
-->          
            <div type="slide">
                <head>September 25: Budapest - Paris - Caen</head>
   <p></p>         </div>
            <!-- 




Pending/20190925_071433.jpg
Pending/20190925_073736.jpg
Pending/20190925_073744.jpg
Pending/20190925_073754.jpg
Pending/20190925_081245.jpg
Pending/20190925_091646.jpg
Pending/20190925_091701.jpg
Pending/20190925_095713.jpg
Pending/20190925_095740.jpg
Pending/20190925_095804.jpg
Pending/20190925_095811.jpg
Pending/20190925_095817.jpg
Pending/20190925_095820.jpg
Pending/20190925_095828.jpg
Pending/20190925_100113.jpg
Pending/20190925_131817.jpg
Pending/20190925_132517.jpg
Pending/20190925_154614.jpg
Pending/20190925_154624.jpg
Pending/20190925_160846.jpg
Pending/20190926_122338.jpg
Pending/20190926_122706.jpg
Pending/20190926_201615.jpg-->
            <div type="slide">

                <!--
Pending/20190927_085946.jpg
Pending/20190927_100922.jpg
Pending/20190927_130324.jpg
Pending/20190927_141749.jpg
Pending/20190927_154554.jpg
Pending/20190927_162627.jpg
Pending/20190928_162921.jpg
Pending/20190928_162923.jpg
-->
                <head>September 27 : Caen - Bristol</head>
                <!--

Sep 26
So this rather fine statue actually also called lou just appeared in the château de caen ...
Image
Image
Dominique roux présents the wonderful #metopes ... Publishing system for scholarly editing

 Oh dear. Storms in la manche mean my plans to come home via jersey have had to be cancelled. #noferry

Sep 27
The good news is I get to catch a proper train instead
On the downside, I an now headed by back to stinky old airport cdg

One of these is for me, if I can only find it #airportsAreHell #flugscham
ImagePlane from paris to Bristol took 55 mins . Bus a2 from airport to centre took 45. 20 min wait for no 8 bus at college green. Something wrong there.


                -->

            </div>



        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
